<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theauraujoh[n] his aurora in tranlagornm in Salem Gloria. Or The discussive of the law and the gospell betwixt the Jew and the Gentile in Salem resurrectionem</title>
            <author>Tany, Thomas, fl. 1649-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T152A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897694</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897694</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170905</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94530)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170905)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2520:18a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theauraujoh[n] his aurora in tranlagornm in Salem Gloria. Or The discussive of the law and the gospell betwixt the Jew and the Gentile in Salem resurrectionem</title>
                  <author>Tany, Thomas, fl. 1649-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 57, [3] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S.B. by Hen. Hills and are to be sold by Giles Calvert at the black spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bound and filmed with Wing T158, T152D, and T156.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jews --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>mystical and geometric images including Star of David, globe and compasses, and descending bird, and Hebrew and alchemical characters</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>THE A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> JOHN His Aurora in Tranlagorum in Salem Gloria.</hi> OR The diſcuſſive of the Law and the Goſpell betwixt the <hi>Jew and the Gentile in Salem Reſurrectionem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Theaurau John. <hi>Allah. Al.</hi> am able to give a definition of all or part of the part, of the Hiſtory or Myſtery in any quaerie ſtated either in the Law or Goſpel, for the reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both into One.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſe and ſhine O Daughter Sion for thy light is come forth from thy God who will honour thee with precious Ornaments of Glory and Dignity.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprematur.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice_on_alphabet">
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I except againſt five letters in the engliſh alphabet as WXYQF and OF is not proper in any ſtate ſubſtantiall, but the four are falſe according to any true ſtate, for a true ſtate cannot be wrote with a falſe letter.</p>
            <p>I write 2 VV for W for X K for Y: I for Q: G for F: PH now C is weak but tis a ſure impeade.</p>
            <p>Now though them letters be wrote it is for to let downe the ſtate to your capacity, but I account them as they are ſtated in the inſert now as the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſtand no tongue in the earth can hold forth the Hebrew as the Engliſh tongue can render it to it ſelfe in the perfection: take notice ſcholars I am not book-learned, but I am heart-knowledged by divine inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>farewell</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="transcribers_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
               </hi> England, O Earth, Jew, Gentile, All ye Nations and People Behold, Behold the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of daies hath ſent you a new day a Gift, Peace and reconciliation in himſelf, in one another: O England and all Nations behold, the king of Righteouſneſs is riſen up in and upon you with healing: that prince of peace to ſettle peace in your borders, O England my love to thee conſtrains me to weepe and to weep bitterly, leaſt thou ſhouldeſt not in this thy day know the things that belong unto thy peace: here's not onely the ſhutting up of an old year, and beginning of a new as to our account, but tis the ſhutting up of thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening of many ages, and the beginning of a new and moſt glorious day, the binding up and caſting away bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken empty veſſels lamps in which is no oyle, doing away ſhaddowes bringing in the ſubſtance, mighty anointings both to Iew and Gentile: God, Chriſt, Iah, Ieſus, Iehovah, Emanuel, Eloah, laying himſelfe the foundation and corner-stone: O England thou art torne from the top to the abyſſe the bottom in thy civill in thy religious conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, who O who ſhall binde thee up; are not thy very foundations rottenneſſe, are not gray hairs upon thee every whee; nay upon all the nations, wherefore hath the Lord done all this, but that he himſelfe might be thy foundation alone: man cannot do Iehovahs work, he indeed may pull down rotten branches, but none can lay foundation but the Lord.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Lord calls for your moſt ſerious and intentive con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and inſpection: ye Jews my Brethren, ye Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles my Brethren be not offended at names, ye Gentiles be not offended at Hi-prieſt, for then you muſt be offended at Chriſt, of whom Paul writes that he was Hi-prieſt, for ever after the order of Melchiſedeck, and that he lives for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Hi-prieſt for ever to make interceſſion for us, he who was without father without mother without beginning of dayes or end of life, who bleſſed Abraham before he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved circumciſion the ſeal of the covenant, Lo the Gentiles —Iſus the Iews Hi-prieſt, nay the Gentiles Ieſus the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles Hi-prieſt alſo: my brethren the Iews ſtumble not, be not offended at the Gentiles Ieſus, who is your Iah your Hi-priest, conſider my dear brethren after whome my ſoul pants: would your God who loved you above all the Nations of the earth give you an Hi-prieſt ſubject to death no it was himſelfe in Aaron, in Moſes, and the reſt, he who lives for ever they could not as men do thoſe mighty works, but twas God even your God Iah, Iehovah the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles Ieſus, that did thoſe great and mighty works in them and by them, both Iew and Gentile brethren agree in this, that there is but one, that this one onely made, and is all things, gives life and being to all things, whither then will the Iew, whither will the Gentile go for life, for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, for deliverance, if there be no other one, but in this one, in whom from whom and by whom are all things even God bleſſed for ever, Iah, Iehovah, Ieſus, all ſpeaking, or ſignifying one and the ſame thing, which is life, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſalvation, to all that in love obey him: the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then lies onely in the outwardneſſe in name and forme, O let us not contend, let us not ſtrive, no differ for or in the things that are not; knowing both have that which is my brethren the Iews have not you in a greater meaſure lost, or are you not much corrupted in the things
<pb facs="tcp:170905:4"/>left unto you by Moſes and Aaron: ſo my brethren the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles is it not now with you, as it was with the Iews about the time that deliverance, that ſalvation aroſe to you, are not the like differences amongſt you now, as was amongſt them then: what true account can you my brethren the Iews give of your institutions, and what true account can you my brethren the Gentiles give of your inſtitutions, if no true account then in truth, and by good conſequence no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count onely hold the foundation God: Thus is both law and Goſpel fully ſlain by that man ſinne, (not of ſinne) and the day of reſurrection is at hand both to Iew and Gentile in one life, in one law: for life which is God, or Christ, or anointing is the law and Goſpel in and unto us.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>This Epiſtle was written by him who tranſcribed this book and is yours in love to ſerve you <hi>ROBERT NORWOOD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>BEloved brethren God hath been pleaſed to manifest himſelfe to me marvelouſly as by this little manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript will appear, if duly conſidered, in as great a meaſure as he did in the times of our forefathers, for there is a light coming forth that all the prophets pointed, unto that is the tranſcendency of reſtoring the Iew and Gentile into one Radax, now for this work hath God ſent me forth, and in this work I am Reuben, the Lords first-borne, and the firſt in the first Trine, as wilappear in the manifeſtation of the diſpenſation: Now I beſcech you my brethren read exactly way carefully, a greater myſtery never was wrote: if rightly underſtood: The Lord give you underſtanding in all things.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to ſerve you in love Theaurau Iohn Tannijour Allah al High-prieſt Sabbah Scribahjail.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="mystical_treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170905:5"/>
            <head>TO THE STATES In <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> and of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved the divine law is in and from God, whoſe Majeſtie none can repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but it doth include all, and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in all and all things: compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending all and all things, and is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of neither all nor nothing, but it ſelfe comprehending, comprehending, comprehending and enjoying it ſelf alone, yet one, no one, but all, no all, yet all, no one, yet one, &amp; that one, that none can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee: This is the perfect Trinity, forth from thence we came, to it we muſt returne againe: This is the working of the three Perſons ſo called in the Deity <hi>in ſeſola in reveras ſed homo, non homo, ſed Deous inſe ſo Pater orbus in elma rationis in ſeſetera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when I cite any language or tongue; know the Major includes the <hi>Minor,</hi> as part Hebrew, part Latin: The Major tis properly wrote in, but I am forced to cite many ſimblims or words for the radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call examplication of the ſentence for no one lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170905:6"/>can carry the truth in its full ſpecies radically: But the <hi>Radaxes</hi> in themſelves which no man can ſpeake: For they are the key and inlet to the Deity, and outlet to his creatived creation and creations know no man created the world, Neither no man gave a law unto the ſame, but Man in his ſtate was the conduit-pipe in which the Deity paſſed through in its own commandings to effect the will of it ſelfe <hi>in ſeſola, non multus lattinnas:</hi> Schollars you think I ſpeak falſe Latin becauſe I follow not learned lying rule: Know a rule cannot be true that is learned, for the rule is life learning and all things: Now how will you have your Rule to be meaſured, this muſt be your anſwer, the learned Fathers and holy men left us this that we walke by, and underſtand one another in: know that a ly with a ly is one method: Now know you cannot read the truth in Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> but your tranſlated ly of <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> know that the difference in the ſtate citing <hi>Jehovah</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very name of him are diſtinct, and no name can hold him that is all things at once and alwayes the ſame for thus in God and of God that is all that can be ſpoken, there is the whole Myſtery of the Deity: ſo the truth in <hi>Auguſtine</hi> could not be wrote, for it was it ſelfe, and the thing and name: now if no man can ſpeake the intentive of the ſpirit of the <hi>Radaxes</hi> Radiaſes is the proper word or ſimblim in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew but the word or ſimblim muſt be ſtated accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Method or language, where it is wrote.</p>
            <p>Now having made introduction into this Myſtery of Myſteries through the light of the eternall being, which is my light and life, in ſo great a meaſure that my humanity cannot underſtand the divinity, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170905:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>have I yet ſtrength to bare it, I am like to a mite to the creation in this myſtery intendant: And to be truly nothing in our ſelves, that is paſſive, is to be wholly Gods all. I beſeech you brethren minde; I cite to you but cannot conferre, for that in me is it ſelfe, the ſame in you, if ye be in God, tis the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one ſpirit, by which we have not onely bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in him, but acceſſe to him in reality.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the Methods Myſtery, tis this: the Deity and humanity, which in effect is all and all things. This is a ſtrange ſtate, but tis a true one, for the humanity is the created of the Deity: Now to begin your tranſlation ſaith <hi>Adam:</hi> Now I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in what time and tongue that derived took both beginning and name, I beſeech you read with circumſpection, for tis the eternall ſpirit dictating forth into the underſtanding, that cauſes a reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the dead; there is one Myſtery that the witneſſes pointed unto that were Preſident: Now this I muſt declare unto the eternall praiſe of the Deity I had no learning <hi>but in ſeven daies when I was a part I received my divine learning by inſpiration ſo that my</hi> light is over all all languages, and truth in them I can read. The ly I leave it to the inventors of it, as for our tranſlation of our divine myſtery (as you call it) the tranſlation is moſt falſe <hi>now for me to aſperſe, and cannot prove it I ſhould be found a falſe witnes before my</hi> God, but becauſe that ſomething you may know I know what I affirme, I have rendred theſe reaſons in <hi>Engliſh</hi> to the capacity of all.</p>
            <p>The firſt the <hi>Radaxes</hi> by men radically under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, they underſtood not.</p>
            <p>Secondly the ſpirit of the <hi>Radaxes,</hi> being unions in themſelves intire, yet their influences being mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170905:7"/>
            <p>Thirdly their conjuncts various.</p>
            <p>Fourthly their adherents intricable.</p>
            <p>Fiftly their intendant extent to this day is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed.</p>
            <p>Sixtly their combines is numerous.</p>
            <p>Seventhly their evangelical life lives in themſelves, which is God, and what to whom he ſends this meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage they are open unto and locked to the whole creation, there is ſeven ſtates ſtated, which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection pointed unto, that the glory of glories that ſhould come unto the <hi>Jews,</hi> the fulneſſe of tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency: in excellency, know you that excellency exceeds tranſcendency: <hi>Tran</hi> carries <hi>in it treas perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> but excellency carries <hi>una perſona</hi> which is the whole 3 in the unions Deity, yet not confounding the three, but in this ſtate the greateſt myſtery, which the world knowes not to this day: The name is not knowledge, knowledge is the the thing and name, and in this I am the Lords <hi>Reuben</hi> in the ſame, and to let you know what <hi>Reuben</hi> is, he is Gods firſt born, that is no leſſe then the evening, and the morne but theſe are hieroglyphiks or ſaffiks to you, but to open your contracted time and name as <hi>Adam,</hi> now if <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was the firſt, where was he placed, the earth he gave to the ſons of men, and then he did not confine man to one place, I argue with you in your own ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dle, though I know how where and when, and what and how what came to be, that is the myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery. Now to your <hi>Adam</hi> I ſtate <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Hamah, and prove this radically radified in all learned learnings, nay your learnings, but to ſhew you your Hebrew is the tenth derivacy of and from the Hebrew radia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and fallen weake by handling, and mingling,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170905:7"/>and worſt of all humanity adding and adjoyning, and weaving in his own invention, that is weaknes, and hath made that a ly which is ſtrength, but it is the ſame and is like a glaſſe that ſhewes him his vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the ſame: now know that to write the Hebrew in full, tis Gods influence in his full creation for, tis word in him, and name on, and in us, the ſubſtance in himſelfe: Now know I write the hebrew in his virgin ſtate, as <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote it, and the ſame ſpirit in me dictating forth what it ſelfe pleaſes to inſert, for we are but ſervants, and pens in its own hand we are weak, nay we are weakeſt men: So the fitteſt to be Gods ſcribes we are nothing, yet in that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingneſſe, is Gods glory moſt illuſtrated to the confounding the learned wiſe men: weak emeane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to confound ſtrong, ſtrongeſt ſtrengths: Now <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote in <hi>Radaxes in voce Evangelorum ſed legit homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> he ſpake in the voice of Angels, and ye read it as men, and by your reading, and indeavour you would bring in your filthy humanity to be ſhearers, in that divine gift alas the more ye reach the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther off, if not reached into firſt, and if reachings do not reach from that divine reached unto you, and that in you reaches at and unto from whence it came out: From this is the true reaching reach, that reaches from, and unto: Minde this laſt ſtate ſtated well: Now to come to our two names <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Hamah:</hi> Now your intention with my truth, is one, but intention is not truth alwayes in its declaratives for the intentions in the heart are truth, but by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward impeads it cannot reach to its declarative, and ſo men judge that a ly which is Gods truth really, and royalty; Minde them words: Now to prove
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170905:8"/>your word <hi>Adam,</hi> thus I know now the leſſe learned the beſt and greateſt ſcholler, now you ſtate <hi>Adam</hi> as one man, Iſtate <hi>Hamah</hi> the man and whole creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Now Doctors I am the Doctor I am in your method thus a man is but one man I grant that, but that man of many compounds, you will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny me this, now to know not ſome compounds of and in man, but to know al and every mite of and in man in its adjunct and coatrifyings which are vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of varieties: I give you one hint in the <hi>primum mobulis,</hi> that ſay you is the ſoul of man, or ſpirit: The firſt I deny, and grant the ſecond, that is the ſoul in which is the <hi>preterparfuiſſe,</hi> and to that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs one hundred and fifty creatives and yet they give not life <hi>in ſexa aurialis: In cophi</hi> or the heart is belonging 63 creatives, and yet no life <hi>ſexta ne vo I ah</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo in the reſt of and in man is creatives but this is by the way now to come to prove you name, for the man I acknowledge to be Gods creation, but for God to put a falſe name, on a true created, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand with his eſſentiall being, for as he is the truth ſo his ſpelling and names are direct truth, for let me tell you the ſpellings of God are the gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his creative and joyning them together is the gatherings created now into himſelfe, then the name he gives them is himſelfe, &amp; can this be a falſe adjoyning or conjoyning but this is myſterious: But to come to your <hi>Adam Adam:</hi> Now whether 4 let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or 5 be more ſignificant judge ye as two did: now I ſay in the true ſpelling there is nod at all ד daleth is animpeade, and in no method bears radical ſoundnes, though in his ſtate he is as proper &amp; perfect as any of the reſt, but thus you ſay God made man perfect, tis true, then how can an impeade be in this perfect
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170905:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>thing, or ſpell this perfect thing, I would deſire all you learned men in the earth to give me the radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Radaxes</hi> of your <hi>Adam,</hi> and then in a moment I would declare my <hi>Hamah</hi> and ye be ſo weak that you cannot ſpell the name, why was fained a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for the ſame, but ſeeming pleaſant fruite is the tree, but time will not beare the unlocking of this myſtery which I ſhall do ſhortly, in your printed Hebrew as you call it, for tis but call indeed, and call is weakneſſe, and a ly, your points and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſimblims or letters.</p>
            <p>(Or letters as you call them) declare patching, and peecing, and indeed tis ſo, ſo I ſay the fathers fathers conceived vanity, and the ſons bring forth the ly? Now to come to that divine law, which are we men, if we be in the truth, for the law is but name, man is the law and thing, and name, Now man cannot be without himſelfe can he, no he is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; eſſentialy himſelfe thus as he is Gods repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative, radically he is one of &amp; in himſelfe, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting from himſelfe is the diviſion, &amp; I may ſay truly to indetractation from his eſſential being, for he hath annihilated himſelfe in that he being himſelfe he would be more, not <hi>in reſpicie ſanctus, ſed in multa divicies, ſed etiam non probat devinies, ſed mors ſola in re in humitantibus in que ſola eſt vita, non loquiter, verbuſus voce, ſed nullos ad me ſola gloria in ſanturum ſpiritus, ſola me opertet ad me,</hi> the engliſh: Not in reſpect of being more holy then he was, but he an holineſſe did conceive, which was riches nay life, but it proved poverty and death, for there is a life in all things, if life were reſtored in us, but we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead things to us that are alive in themſelves
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170905:9"/>is dead to us, ſo our injoyment is ſorrow, travell and teares, and trouble, there is the wages of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience: nay to all this the prieſts by ſubtill pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy hath let in another Devill to torment us when we are dead, and hell to plague us in; To fright us to themſelves which is Abaddon, or Apollyon, but I wave this till another time: here ly es the bondage of the creation a derivacy from this ש wrote in the greek the oldeſt greek which you will ſay muſt be neareſt; now the differance betwixt the <hi>Indian</hi> greek and your greek is quite another thing in ſound and ſubſtance, this that you deifie ſo much, your eſſence your trade, for I; account it no better, nay when the maſters of your own company was in power how many that would not hear a ly told was troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and excommunicated, but God hath cut off the head of the <hi>Abadoniſme</hi> and I hope nay I know I ſhall binde up the <hi>Abbre,</hi> and chain up that decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Devill that hath deceived the nations ſo long now if you ſay I am againſt teaching, I anſwer I cannot for the true teacher is God, and he makes an inlet for himſelfe in his new creature, or elſe he is in darkneſſe: you will ſay what was not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles teachers of God, and miniſters of the goſpel; I ſay no they were diſpenſers of the eternall work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God in them to the ſame where it met, it was, nay and is the ſame, an union in one ſpirit, they ſpoke from the root, you from the name of their dead letter, you ſay <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid ſo, yea and it is the word of God, God is word himſelf, &amp; not a lettered name, <hi>Paul</hi> was word you have not <hi>Paul's</hi> letters ſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, then you are far <hi>from Pauls</hi> word, nay my brethren ye prieſts, ye have a truth within you, and yet a ly, nay
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170905:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ly is preached by you, for the ſpellings of a ly cannot teach truth, but tis darke to you, and for you I cite it, to cauſe you to look into your ſelves: now to cite one place in <hi>Matthew</hi> the firſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> verſe that is an alluſive to the whole method intended in the whole book; now where will you find this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is not <hi>Matthew,</hi> tis in Saint <hi>Luke</hi> the 5 and the 18 verſe tis not there tis in Saint <hi>John</hi> that is his third epiſtle was wrote by <hi>Matthew</hi> as ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for love is God: now what greater love was there then this God ſent himſelfe to redeeme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: who could captivate God, is not he all unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable, then who is Gods oppoſer, the Devil what is the Devil, tis not love, where doth he dwel, in the hearst nay ſpirits of men: when ſhall he be caſt out, at the appearing of God, which is the burning up of ſin in man, but to prove <hi>Matthew</hi> the firſt, <hi>Luke</hi> the 5 and <hi>John</hi> the 3 thus: <hi>Matthew, Luke,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> was one ſpirit, and in them one birth in the Trine, and all in one another, and every one diſtinct by name, yet the thing one, there is neither one nor a thouſand nor a Million of Millions: for the whole creation to him is but one man, was, is, and ſhall be light the ſame, darkneſſe the ſame, but diſtinct from one another: thus the Lord doth unfold him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in ſome more, in ſome leſſe but the ſame ſpirit in all light to him but dark in and to our ſelves: Now to know how this darkneſſe came and continues on, and over the face of the new creature, the new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not at firſt able to unvaile that thick and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy vaile that lyes upon it, why becauſe the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is not able to bear it at once or many times dayes and years: not but that he was able to have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170905:10"/>made us able, but tis his pleaſure ſo to make us, and in thus being made our happines conſiſts in ſo being content, then in truth his will is done in earth as in heaven, this is obedience to the law nay tis the divine law in us, obedience is our royalty, our glory, our Majeſty, our excellency, our union in him, with our ſelves, and with one another, this is love, this is God in us unto himſelfe, for God is love: Now <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> complaines of oppreſſion, of injuſtice, and wickedneſſe, what would he have done in theſe dayes fours; who covenant in lyes to deſtroy, <hi>O I weep for to ſee it, my ſoul is in heavineſſe, and my tears flow continually for the afflicted,</hi> and deliverance ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears not in power, ariſe O Lord our God, and plead our cauſe againſt our oppreſſors, and deliver thy choſen we are neceſſitated to them that hate us, and thy law which is love they condemne: Now to account that to be which is not is to imbrace the ly, and let truth paſſe, thus to ſay we act righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we wrong God, but to ſpeak truth though we cannot helpe people to the enjoyment of it, we are innocent when we do not bid God ſpeed to their wicked works: Now what doth a man get in, and among wicked men, reproach and infamy, and counted the worſt of men, though in truth they can charge him with no crime, how are we termed <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> and laſcivious and wicked: in this matter I anſwer for my ſelfe, as the anſwer of another will not free me. Now know I have been rent, and divided among many, and my day of healing is not come from my God to me as yet, but it draweth near, for I ſee hope in this loweſt duſt: Now to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my ſelfe I hate every evil vvay not by quivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170905:10"/>but in truth as thus if I were not what I ſeem to be, Nay more then I can expreſſe, how could I be the Lords Hi-prieſt, and holy writer of the law which is love as theſe words import <hi>allah al Sabbah Scribah jail:</hi> Now know I never was any ſchollar I could read Engliſh: In 7 dayes I was abſent ſaw no man, and in that time my God taught me, that now I am able to tranſlate the Bible to it ſelfe which is truth, then inſert that truth into any language un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven, and yet not a quarter of a year ſince I came forth, My light is dayly more and more, yet I am ſent to the <hi>Iews</hi> my brethren: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw ſomething when he ſaid rejoyce ye Gentiles with his people now is the returne to the <hi>Iews,</hi> which have been out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly caſt off, but inward obedience is the ſweet ſmelling ſavoured ſacrifice, the undeniable truth on both ſides as <hi>Abraham</hi> believed and it is Righteouſneſſe, the thing ſpoken from the Lord, is word and that word is reſtoration to life from the dead, which word is <hi>obedience that is love O wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, wonderfull, the Jew in obedience love:</hi> that love is God, the Gentile which word ſignifies an unbeliever, <hi>the unbeleever turned obedient obedience is love, love is God, here is the Jew in God,</hi> the Gentile turn'd Jew, and in God, where is the differance, tis in the name, what is the name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and Jeſus, I am a <hi>Jew</hi> my Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus is the <hi>Jews Jehovah the Iews Iehovah my Ieſus, theſe two are but names of the ſame intended thing,</hi> Thing is the ſubſtance of both the names. Now my brethren <hi>the Iews</hi> by line cannot reliſh the name Jeſus, nor the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile cannot own the law, Now what is the law tis the goſpel, what is the goſpel tis the law, the law is goſpel being true revealed the goſpel is law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170905:11"/>the goſpel is hid <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to them that are without: <hi>Now you have tranſlated O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RECO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, that was Pauls words that his lips pronounced,</hi> and you have ſtated an irrecoverable eſtate upon that, which <hi>Paul</hi> intended not, he was better inſtructed then to ſtate a final ſentence, and difinition, on that him ſelfe lay under not long before, but the word runs thus in <hi>Pauls</hi> true method, <hi>if light be hid, tis to them that are without:</hi> Now minde the difference, <hi>if the goſpel be hid it is to them that are loſt,</hi> what work is in this text, can all your wit wave this cited tranſlation, you cannot for your affirmaive wil admit no negoſiation, but bindes up finally, which <hi>Paul</hi> durſt not do he had the root, you not the leaves that grew of the twigs, therefore examine the reſt, and you will finde no more odds but darkneſſe ſtated for light in many places.</p>
            <p>Now here is hope for all that was in darkneſſe—<hi>then which the Iews was moſt oppoſit then, becauſe the manifeſtation of Ieſus was freſh before them as I may ſay,</hi> and there was hope of their greater obedience <hi>Paul</hi> thought, and therefore he ſtated many invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that the word held forth dubiouſly, as the Scripture is all myſtery, as I ſhall open by and by in this little treatiſe <hi>to come to the law Paul our Apostle ſaith tis holy, juſt, and good, Christ ſaith I came not to deſtroy the law but to fulfill</hi> by what, by obedience, <hi>is obedience the fulfilling the law,</hi> then remember <hi>Moſes</hi> my ſervant, and the commandements I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him as my mouth ſpeaking to you, <hi>that is you ſhould obey me and keep my commands for ever:</hi> Now let us reaſon as men, for we underſtand ever to be alwayes, and we are not guilty in not knowing,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170905:11"/>
               <hi>but knowledge makes us guilty, for light is come but men love darkneſſe,</hi> that is not departing from that, and turning to that, <hi>light points them unto: Now what have you Gentiles gotten with your upbraiding the Iews with their darkneſſe,</hi> it preaches to you the greater deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for it had been better you had not ſeen then in ſeeing not obeying, for <hi>Christ is light, the law is light;</hi> Now the <hi>obedience</hi> to theſe <hi>makes us it, and it us,</hi> and ſo <hi>an union with the father,</hi> all which is but <hi>obedience:</hi> but to come nearer <hi>thus Christ</hi> ſay we, <hi>is our rule,</hi> which light is truth, <hi>the anointed of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, now if ye walke contrary to his preſcript</hi> ye are not <hi>ruled</hi> by <hi>him</hi> nor by <hi>his light,</hi> then take your own tranſlated text, <hi>if the goſpel be hid, tis to them that be loſt:</hi> Now they may in a proper ſence be ſaid to be <hi>loſt,</hi> that have <hi>had light;</hi> acknowledged it to be the <hi>light,</hi> and they in <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> that walke not in that <hi>light,</hi> when that <hi>light is utter darkneſſe to themſelves,</hi> O poor ſouls I pitty you in this <hi>that you think you are rich, and need nothing, not knowing you are poor blinde, and naked,</hi> is Chriſt <hi>your hope,</hi> your glorying glory? alas, he is the ſubſtance of that lettered name: he <hi>commands love</hi> ye are <hi>murderers,</hi> he commands, <hi>do work of mercy, how many ſtarve for want of bread?</hi> he ſaith <hi>cloth,</hi> how many naked? O leave off the name, and in your obedience purſue the <hi>thing, in new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> by better declarative <hi>acts,</hi> tis a diſhonour to name <hi>Ieſus</hi> to act in other wayes, are theſe the <hi>good</hi> works <hi>of the goſpel</hi> that ſhould <hi>joyne</hi> &amp; bring in <hi>unbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi> No, you <hi>put them by</hi> that would come in, and indeed are <hi>enemies to Chriſt, and put him,</hi> in as much as in you lyes, <hi>to open ſhame;</hi> but you hurt your <hi>ſelves</hi> not him; for he is, <hi>ye are not.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170905:12"/>
            <p>Now I come to the <hi>Iew</hi> my <hi>brethren according to the fleſh,</hi> they are <hi>darke: light</hi> is coming to them, and <hi>freedome</hi> too, from their <hi>outward bondage, to a glorious freedome:</hi> Now though there is darkneſſe, yet there is <hi>love one to another,</hi> if we ſay <hi>darkneſſe, and fruits of love proceed,</hi> is not that <hi>darkneſſe</hi> better then our <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>doing nothing?</hi> Minde that ſtate; well may that ſpeak for them, that if <hi>more light,</hi> more <hi>works;</hi> now we run <hi>contrary,</hi> the more we <hi>know</hi> the leſſe we <hi>do,</hi> but to turne to the <hi>vaſte difference,</hi> that is betwixt theſe <hi>two people</hi> ſo called, that is <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> under which ſtate the whole creation lies <hi>intitled,</hi> that though men <hi>account many,</hi> yet to the <hi>Lord</hi> but one <hi>people,</hi> yet two <hi>diſtinct, light</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> now the <hi>Iew</hi> is the <hi>ſeed</hi> to whom the <hi>promiſe was made, ſaying in thy ſeed ſhall all the earth rejoyce</hi> was this made to <hi>Abraham</hi> when he was <hi>circumciſed</hi> or before? <hi>before,</hi> for <hi>obedience</hi> led him to the <hi>act:</hi> Now <hi>faith was before circumciſion,</hi> and <hi>circumciſion was a ſeale to Abraham of the Ty</hi> or <hi>Covenant betwixt God and him:</hi> now know <hi>circumciſion</hi> was not a <hi>vaine thing,</hi> becauſe it was the <hi>declarative act</hi> of <hi>obedience</hi> of <hi>the father of the faithfull</hi> now we own <hi>Abraham</hi> to be the <hi>father</hi> of us both <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> then if you be both <hi>ſons</hi> where is your <hi>obedience</hi> to your <hi>father,</hi> that <hi>commanded his children to walke in his wayes,</hi> and his wayes was Gods way, and what he <hi>commanded,</hi> his God <hi>commanded him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to come to the full ſtate of <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> tis thus the <hi>name</hi> cauſes the <hi>difference</hi> &amp; not the <hi>ſubſtance;</hi> but the <hi>maine is,</hi> they being not in the <hi>being is light</hi> is the cauſe of the <hi>cenſuring</hi> one another, for they that be in that being never <hi>diſputes,</hi> for to <hi>be</hi> is to end <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes;</hi> and not to <hi>be,</hi> is all <hi>diſputes;</hi> So then the <hi>ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170905:12"/>diſpute: the <hi>ſubstance</hi> is <hi>one</hi> and both in <hi>one;</hi> and ſo there is <hi>union</hi> and <hi>communion with our God; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iew nor Gentile, neither circumciſion, nor uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, but a new creature, and this</hi> that creates this <hi>new creature</hi> is <hi>obedience:</hi> now if obedience be the <hi>Ty</hi> that is required of all, nay, it was the Ty on your <hi>Adam,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> my <hi>Hamah</hi> which is the ſame intended, now to be <hi>obedient</hi> is the <hi>reſtored being,</hi> for <hi>diſobedience</hi> caſt out, and <hi>obedience</hi> brings in; here the <hi>depth</hi> of <hi>myſtery</hi> lies to know how <hi>loſt?</hi> how <hi>reſtored?</hi> we fell, we all in <hi>Hamah</hi> that is <hi>Adam,</hi> your bible reades it ſo: now the <hi>Iews</hi> law ſaith <hi>do this and tis life,</hi> what is the meaning of that? was it <hi>dubiouſly laid down?</hi> then the people could not be <hi>guilty;</hi> but tis as the <hi>Radaxes</hi> are every one <hi>distinct and perfect unity in it ſelfe,</hi> and joyned tis the fame; ſo was al Gods <hi>declaratives</hi> to his <hi>people;</hi> for <hi>people</hi> could not have been charged with <hi>guilty,</hi> but by <hi>diſobedience,</hi> and they knowing clearly the <hi>command</hi> was <hi>contrary</hi> to that <hi>that they would act,</hi> now tis properly ſtated: <hi>ſed hominibus in ſe ſpetiam in regulative ſed nam meam orata alvahin obedeunter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaret ad me mecum, ad me ſolah ſonat and at ono pon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah allah nedet ad me male one ſeraret oloco ſolam per hoc oli medat in aquieſſe:</hi> the Engliſh: but men in all things would diſobey me <hi>ſetting up themſelves</hi> that I <hi>command</hi> not, but to obey me in that <hi>light</hi> I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto them, but they denied me in all, and ſo became nothing of me, but reſt <hi>in themſelves,</hi> which is no reſt, but <hi>death</hi> to that, ſhould have been <hi>life:</hi> that is their <hi>injoyment ſorrow</hi> and <hi>miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you ſcollars that view my book titled <hi>Aurora Tranlagorum:</hi> now know you know not my learning, you learne it, but tis <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>learning;</hi> there
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170905:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>is <hi>learning,</hi> I count the <hi>parrets</hi> learning, that is <hi>head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learning,</hi> without <hi>heart-knowledge:</hi> now know when Icite, any <hi>Latin, Hebrew, or Greek, or Arabick, or Siri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack, or tranſilvanian, or Muſcovian, or Orcadialis, Orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis,</hi> in any one of theſe with anyone word I can <hi>influ the whole ſentence,</hi> I can impede the whole <hi>ſentence, or any word in the ſentence</hi> ſtating it betwixt two <hi>Radical words, in any method I can leſſen</hi> or weaken the <hi>Ty</hi> of any <hi>Bar</hi> in what <hi>word</hi> or <hi>letter</hi> or <hi>ſentence,</hi> I pleaſe and if you cannot do this, you cannot write true: you know ג <hi>gimell</hi> is the Hebrew <hi>key, kion</hi> the <hi>greek</hi> key E the Engliſh <hi>Radicall,</hi> but you know not this <hi>method,</hi> nor none ſhall know it, <hi>but he to whom it is ſent</hi> if you were not <hi>ſtupid</hi> in <hi>ignorance,</hi> you might <hi>know me,</hi> and from whence I <hi>come;</hi> and my <hi>work</hi> is the <hi>greateſt</hi> on the <hi>whole Globe,</hi> for to bring <hi>variety</hi> into <hi>unity; but</hi> not to <hi>diſpute, but to give a state,</hi> or take a <hi>ſtate,</hi> in any <hi>created thing or things;</hi> in <hi>Earth, Aire, fire,</hi> or <hi>water, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restriall, Ce eſtiall, the influences</hi> of the <hi>starres: But to the matter of obedience,</hi> it is a <hi>due</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> and to be paid by us who are his <hi>leage-people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to conſider that <hi>diſobedience caſts forth, and obedience is an inlet to happineſſe; now ſee how many purſues the one, and flies from the other; now we are blind</hi> in <hi>diſobeying,</hi> and ſeeing is to obey; tis the light of <hi>life,</hi> the glory of Excellency, the <hi>divine truth,</hi> the <hi>law,</hi> the <hi>goſpell</hi> the <hi>all required of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now know who requires it? God; for what? For our good;</hi> and ſhall we be ſuch <hi>en emies</hi> to our <hi>ſelves as not to retrune to our happineſſe? O Lord helpe us we are a helpleſſe lump, a ſtupid ignorance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>main difference</hi> betwixt the <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tileis,</hi> when they <hi>neither of them are in light; for dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170905:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſpute <hi>names,</hi> and take it for <hi>things,</hi> but to be in light is an end of <hi>diſputes:</hi> for light is the <hi>ſubstance</hi> and cannot <hi>stoop to ſhaddowes or notions:</hi> Now to be in <hi>light,</hi> is to be the <hi>children of Abraham:</hi> Then <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> both one; and both <hi>reſtored Hamahs</hi> or <hi>Addams</hi> by obedience in him.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the <hi>point</hi> of <hi>points,</hi> nay the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum mobile,</hi> is this that cauſes the <hi>farre diſſent</hi> of the <hi>Jew</hi> from the <hi>Gentile,</hi> is the <hi>humanity of Chriſt:</hi> now know <hi>faith</hi> goes not <hi>to ſeek an</hi> author, for tis the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> and tries all: now let us look into the <hi>devini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and the <hi>humanity</hi> of <hi>Ieſus</hi> and be <hi>circumſpect</hi> that by the <hi>one we confound</hi> not the <hi>other:</hi> tis a <hi>myſtery</hi> to this <hi>day,</hi> the <hi>Apostles</hi> they could not reach the <hi>heighth,</hi> and is it ſo eaſy to <hi>us</hi> that are <hi>blinde to them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now Christ is the glory of the father; by him created he the world; he is the life of the world; without him made he nothing that was made: equall with the father:</hi> now I deny any man can reach <hi>theſe,</hi> or any one of <hi>theſe;</hi> tis not what <hi>another ſaies,</hi> but the matter what I know; now this I <hi>know</hi> this very day, I have the greateſt reach in this that any <hi>man on the globe hath;</hi> and yet I reach not full, this is the <hi>divinity,</hi> the <hi>huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> is harder to <hi>define;</hi> now <hi>Chriſt the firſt borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many brethren,</hi> this text is wrong <hi>rendred;</hi> for the <hi>Antecedent</hi> goes before the <hi>relative,</hi> as <hi>hos in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troas</hi> in a <hi>lagma in a ſaleph in rem fratris,</hi> tis in his full <hi>intendant,</hi> he was the <hi>birth</hi> of the firſt <hi>brethren</hi> know my <hi>knowledge</hi> tranſcends the <hi>tranſlated coppies;</hi> as I ſhall ſhortly ſhew in my next <hi>book,</hi> which will be the <hi>Elementary alſabs:</hi> now I ſhall <hi>cite</hi> a <hi>cite</hi> that was never <hi>cited</hi> yet: he was the firſt in the <hi>firſt trine</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceding, you underſtand not this <hi>myſtery, he was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170905:14"/>the anointed of God,</hi> that text holds <hi>pertinent to the ſtate,</hi> but not rendred in full; but I paſſe that; he died <hi>for us (ſaith the text)</hi> that text is <hi>falſely tranſtated</hi> from the very <hi>roote,</hi> and another <hi>thing ſtated,</hi> for the <hi>thing intended;</hi> the word in the true orthodox is theſe, <hi>ver non homo ſed in loca pancaveret</hi> a man not a man but in place of offence. <hi>Now</hi> look I beſeech you all into this dubious text, and conclude not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore due examination, that text ſtands in entire <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> and admits of no <hi>adjunct</hi> of any other <hi>language:</hi> ye have your <hi>derivacy</hi> from the <hi>greek,</hi> that hath <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated</hi> the intended <hi>myſtery:</hi> tis derived from this <hi>eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> in the greek <hi>ous te annagramon in ſem ſeala alar o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phone adriei ſebat,</hi> this is the true greek intendant to their ſtate, but tis true wrote from the Hebrew <hi>Radaxes</hi> as is here inſerted, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I peat that laſt for your <hi>nodification;</hi> but Tread without it, and never uſe no <hi>broken, patched, peeces</hi> of Radaxes to inſert I know not what as you do conſtantly; now you may lay on the ſame bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den again, and diſpute for it you may, know what you will finde in me, though I cite no more on the affirmative: <hi>He ſitteth on the right hand of God to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede for us; is not this open to the world what is made here? but I paſſe till time, that truth may take place; while then I amſilent:</hi> though I know God wilconfound all men; that the glory may be unto himſelfe, not <hi>by might nor by power, but by my word will I over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them ſaith the Lord my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now if light be come from heaven to light</hi> the <hi>dark corners of the earth, let us rejoyce</hi> and <hi>give glory;</hi> for <hi>great things are at hand,</hi> do you think it is <hi>in vaine fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> that <hi>people run to and fro in this City crying wo and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170905:14"/>vengeance,</hi> I my ſelfe was forced to go and cry in the ſtreets, <hi>wo unto this bloody City it ſhall be deſtroy'd; but becauſe vengeance is not executed ſuddenly, therefore are the hearts of the ſonnes of men ſet on fire to do wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> though we declare a time, and the <hi>time</hi> come not, know it effects its own end, <hi>and the wicked go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on more wickedly, to make himſelfe fit for the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> we, ſit down and acknowledge what is truth is Gods, &amp; <hi>that that</hi> is the <hi>ly</hi> is our <hi>ſelves:</hi> &amp; we are ſilent till the Lord appear <hi>to refreſh our fainting ſpirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to come to this <hi>ſtate</hi> betwixt <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> now the <hi>humanity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> it doth ſtumble the <hi>Iew:</hi> now let me ſpeak; the <hi>humanity</hi> hath been ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with <hi>humane hands, and heads</hi> that it doth in a manner <hi>darken</hi> the <hi>divinity of Chriſt,</hi> as I could ſhew in divers places, and confound <hi>all, and all men,</hi> I weigh the <hi>Creation</hi> as a <hi>feather</hi> in the <hi>divine myſtery;</hi> for I am the Lords <hi>gimell:</hi> ſchollers you know that <hi>unlocking,</hi> and <hi>locking</hi> is all <hi>myſtery</hi> in the whole <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and none <hi>reaching me,</hi> if they could I was not fit to be the <hi>Lords Hi-prieſt:</hi> now the Iews ſtand off through you <hi>Gentiles diſorderly walking, now where ſo much light</hi> in <hi>words</hi> is acknowledged to be, and ſuch <hi>fruits</hi> flow, that <hi>light</hi> for the effects are the <hi>declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of our inward roote; <hi>for by their fruite you ſhall know them:</hi> now to give a <hi>declarative</hi> of that that ſhould be the <hi>Crown</hi> of a <hi>beleevers acting,</hi> truly I <hi>bluſh</hi> and am <hi>aſham'd</hi> to declare it; becauſe if the <hi>power</hi> that muſt bring in the <hi>Iews</hi> where not <hi>ſtronger then</hi> that <hi>power of darkneſſe that rules in moſt of you,</hi> I ſhould beat them quite <hi>OFF, but they are grafted in by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Almighty,</hi> and that <hi>ingrafting</hi> ſhall appear in <hi>glory to your ſhame,</hi> that <hi>ſeem,</hi> and are not; but are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170905:15"/>of the <hi>ſynagogue of Satan</hi> that deceiver to deal <hi>plainly</hi> with you who have been the <hi>great profeſſors,</hi> how are you <hi>fallen?</hi> How is your <hi>glory</hi> turned into <hi>ſhame?</hi> nay many of you (I may ſay) are unmand; this is ſtrange but will appear too true in the <hi>incluſo;</hi> Now you are <hi>falſſifiers of covenant,</hi> ye are covetous <hi>oppreſſors unjuſt,</hi> having reſpect to your <hi>ſelves,</hi> unreſpecting all others; ye are <hi>adulterers,</hi> and <hi>whore-mongers;</hi> nay <hi>unſatiable,</hi> worſe then beaſts; O that <hi>man</hi> ſhould ſo farre <hi>unman</hi> his <hi>noble ſpirit!</hi> that his <hi>declaratives</hi> prove more <hi>ignorant</hi> then a <hi>beaſt;</hi> nay <hi>many of ye will</hi> plead for it, I ſay, as ever I ſaid tis luſt, <hi>love</hi> is <hi>love,</hi> whoſe end is <hi>love:</hi> I ſhall declare two points to try this by as I have ever affirm'd the ſame.</p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>O man</hi> I ſpeak to <hi>thee</hi> who art the head, thou art the <hi>male,</hi> thou <hi>comeſt</hi> to the <hi>female,</hi> and through thy <hi>perſwaſion</hi> thou <hi>bringest her to thy will:</hi> what this <hi>will</hi> is, <hi>love,</hi> or luſt the effect I commit <hi>to judgement</hi> betwixt me and you; having <hi>attained your will,</hi> ſhe is made thereby uncapable of an <hi>outward ſubſtance:</hi> for very food <hi>ſhe</hi> hath not, <hi>you</hi> to another and <hi>more,</hi> and bring them to the ſame <hi>incapacity,</hi> and never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard any of them at all; nay <hi>ſteal</hi> from <hi>them,</hi> you <hi>love,</hi> you ſay, ſo wel, and <hi>deceive</hi> all that <hi>truſt you;</hi> and this is your practiſe; <hi>doth Christ ſet you ſuch example?</hi> or his <hi>miniſters teach ſo?</hi> now to make your acts <hi>love,</hi> you ought to <hi>want</hi> your <hi>ſelfe,</hi> that the neceſſity, thus laid on <hi>her</hi> might be <hi>releeved;</hi> for <hi>did ever man hate his own fleſh?</hi> Judge ye what I ſay: now your anſwer is <hi>all</hi> is <hi>good, and all is God:</hi> let me make an in let into that <hi>ſeered conſcience,</hi> &amp; <hi>weighye with true weights,</hi> would it be good for you to be ſtarved to death judge ye? <hi>That thou would'ſt do to thy ſelfe, do to another;</hi> this is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170905:15"/>
               <hi>love;</hi> the other is <hi>lust</hi> and this is the <hi>whole required of man,</hi> O this Engliſh <hi>OF</hi> doth all the <hi>miſchiefe</hi> in the vvhole tongue, it is as bad as the <hi>greek Y:</hi> they be tvvo <hi>lying words</hi> holding <hi>dubious varieties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to come to the niſity of diſtinction <hi>in this falſe word, I take this ſtate to state it in: God is good, &amp; OF him</hi> are all things <hi>good,</hi> that word is a <hi>ly,</hi> that <hi>OF him</hi> in that ſtate, the true ſtate according to the divine inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſpirit: You had thought <hi>OF</hi> ſhould have been <hi>placed there,</hi> but it would <hi>vilify</hi> the <hi>intendant:</hi> now <hi>OF God,</hi> is nothing proper to his <hi>divine being;</hi> but <hi>in God</hi> all things are, and <hi>by him all things conſiſt, and exſiſt,</hi> and <hi>in flu,</hi> and are <hi>impeaded</hi> by the ſame pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er here <hi>ſtated:</hi> now you that ſay <hi>all is God, and all is good, in God all are good, from him the ſame,</hi> but this doth not reach your <hi>method;</hi> nor <hi>you: but OF God you</hi> and your <hi>method</hi> is not; now the <hi>state</hi> is contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; tis your true <hi>emblem,</hi> for you are <hi>a contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous generation; your fathers</hi> were <hi>bad,</hi> that was the <hi>Antinomian,</hi> againſt them <hi>Policarpus</hi> did <hi>inveigh; but</hi> ye are worſe then the worſt of them; for ye by <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence</hi> make <hi>Iehovah</hi> nothing at all but a dead idol: nay ſo I may ſay with <hi>reverence</hi> to his <hi>divine majeſty,</hi> you make him your <hi>ſtalking horſe;</hi> that is you <hi>ſhow</hi> him, to <hi>betray</hi> them that look on him: that is <hi>the poor innocent; he or ſhe</hi> is <hi>devoured</hi> and <hi>deſtroyed</hi> by <hi>you: this I know:</hi> but to the <hi>niſity</hi> of <hi>distinction OF,</hi> tis certed for a <hi>negative,</hi> and is underſtood an <hi>affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and here is in theſe <hi>two letters a miſchievous myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; wounding when they are intended healings</hi> Now <hi>of God,</hi> and <hi>in God,</hi> are two <hi>diſtincts</hi> as <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe:</hi> now to ſay, to be <hi>in God,</hi> is proper; but to ſay to be of God, is improper; now to bring the neareſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that can be ſtated is this, <hi>God is the father of us
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170905:16"/>all,</hi> that ſtate is non-ſence and a ly; as thus, God is the father of all, that is falſe according to divine writing: for as God is <hi>truth,</hi> ſo all muſt, every letter ſtated, and ſyllable, word and every conjunct, and adjunct, conjoyned, and adjoyned in meeter and method: alas men <hi>blinde cannot diſcerne cullers,</hi> nor <hi>humane learning</hi> fathom <hi>divine knowledge</hi> which is knowledge and learning, is a <hi>ly</hi> without the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation which is <hi>God himſelfe,</hi> now to ſhew the full face of this <hi>dubious conſtellation</hi> that is (of) you would think it quickly done, that (q) is another of the <hi>duplexes</hi> to be caſt out when I come to my maine <hi>work,</hi> that is the tranſlations of the hidden <hi>truth</hi> that lies <hi>vilifyed</hi> in the <hi>ly</hi> which is the greek <hi>tongue,</hi> now our forefathers deſired, <hi>but no man was found worthy to open the book,</hi> but the <hi>ſpirit</hi> that <hi>indicted it:</hi> if the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Jeſus</hi> or <hi>Iehovah</hi> be in <hi>you, he is the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiter of his own intendants</hi> intended in the divine and ſacred evangelical expreſſing in <hi>almo Bonoſo almare ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ophronorico ab ſe ſola amantur albo boano ſo on abciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſere nos peca oet nedet almahoſanneh alujah hah eli lo mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodinei el le avellet ad me hoſaret peco oli bedeneret:</hi> the engliſh of theſe five languages cited, &amp; all compoſure inunionsunion.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>The hidden depths are open making</l>
               <l>to raiſe ſleeping men to a waking,</l>
               <l>to raiſe them from their ſecurity</l>
               <l>and ſcale their eyes to ſee eternity.</l>
               <l>And that great deep reveal'd to them:</l>
               <l>that troubleſome <hi>mountain,</hi> and hidden <hi>stem.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>that ſtar of <hi>glory</hi> in the skie</l>
               <l>that's <hi>buried</hi> by mans <hi>incredulity.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170905:16"/>
            <p>Now to ſtate the thing that is of; and (In:) <hi>oF,</hi> is aquiet <hi>aſſeveration</hi> from any intendant, as of ſuch a thing, ſuch a thing is that is proper; for, to ſay that this <hi>thing is</hi> or was <hi>of</hi> that <hi>thing is the negative, denying the afirmative, ſo by conſequence nothing</hi> at all but non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; God will not be ſpelled ſo: thus to ſay <hi>this</hi> was ſuch a mans <hi>ſon</hi> tis proper, but to ſay <hi>this is</hi> the <hi>ſon</hi> of ſuch a man; the <hi>firſt</hi> denies the <hi>ſecond,</hi> and ſo no <hi>concluſive</hi> can be made: Now to you <hi>Antenomen,</hi> that is your name: proper tis to you, for by acts men <hi>declare,</hi> and your <hi>acts</hi> declare you to be the worſt of <hi>beaſts, wolves</hi> in ſheeps-clothing; now you are <hi>of God,</hi> but not in <hi>God:</hi> now to this you ſay, <hi>all is God,</hi> and <hi>all is good;</hi> how will this hold with your actings? thus you may ſay <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> is not <hi>of God,</hi> but by him tis <hi>ſuffered,</hi> or elſe you could not have a being: now God is <hi>good</hi> to all; tis his <hi>eſſentiall</hi> being, he muſt <hi>ceaſe</hi> to be, if he ceaſe to be <hi>good,</hi> this I grant you: but what will this helpe you, nothing at all, but loade you the more; that God is <hi>good</hi> and hath <hi>commanded</hi> you <hi>good</hi> wayes for you to walke in, and a <hi>declarative</hi> of that good law in you, being <hi>Gods,</hi> ought to be <hi>expreſſed</hi> by a good <hi>warrantable walking</hi> before this <hi>good God, or elſe you are found fighters againſt your own mercy:</hi> ſo much for that ſecond LY: <hi>all is God</hi> now here the point ſtated is more curious then <hi>oF,</hi> (and <hi>IN</hi>) thus all is God; tis true in one ſence, but your eyes <hi>reaches</hi> not that <hi>center:</hi> for your <hi>eyes looks downward,</hi> your actings declare no leſſe: <hi>properly</hi> and <hi>eſſentially</hi> all things are <hi>God,</hi> for from him all things are and came, this I grant you; but this I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny you: your <hi>carnall reaſon</hi> is of and from your ſelfe, as you are an <hi>eſſentiall,</hi> being from that eſſential, eſſentially deſcended: minde I intreat for the myſtery is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170905:17"/>great, now from your eſſentiall there is in you, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall, deſentives,</hi> in <hi>concurring</hi> with that that is not, or with that that is <hi>truth;</hi> now the ſtate is fixed on its peremphiſis; now the querie is to be reſolved; <hi>for theſe things am I ſent forth involved in humanity,</hi> and not <hi>humanity</hi> but <hi>divinity;</hi> not mingling with humanity, but am in my own <hi>divinity</hi> intire, free, abſolute, <hi>unneceſſitated,</hi> yet acting perfect truth it ſelfe: Brethren here I ſee ſomething to high for me to underſtand: I ſay, as I ſaid before, I am but <hi>pen</hi> to this <hi>anointing,</hi> the more I ſee the appearance, the leſſe I am in my <hi>ſelfe:</hi> O Lord ſtrengthen my <hi>huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> for thy <hi>divinity</hi> is a <hi>burden</hi> to me, and cauſes my <hi>humanity</hi> to waſte in <hi>tears</hi> continually: Now you <hi>Antinomians,</hi> you create to your ſelves a <hi>LY:</hi> and that you <hi>deifie</hi> as <hi>God,</hi> and it is let in the <hi>ſeat of God,</hi> and is not God thus you ſay <hi>God is good,</hi> ſo ſay I, but go to <hi>diſtinctions</hi> to diſtinguiſh to a title, and <hi>you</hi> and <hi>all</hi> ſhall ſee you are <hi>nothing in God,</hi> but <hi>of God,</hi> and <hi>by God</hi> you are ſuffered in your <hi>evill wayes;</hi> thus Gods <hi>goodneſſe</hi> is nothing to you; for you take a <hi>goodneſſe</hi> to your <hi>ſelves,</hi> refuſing his goodneſſe; and chuſe you one of your own as I will declare: for the point is wonderous great, and a <hi>gulfe</hi> ſwallowing <hi>many,</hi> and more will <hi>follow,</hi> that <hi>ſeeming pleaſant paths, but they lead to destruction; ſtolen bread is ſweet, but bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the latter end:</hi> now to your <hi>created God</hi> of your own making, did not they in the old time worſhip ſtocks and ſtones? do not you <hi>Goſpellers</hi> worſe? for you worſhip the <hi>Devill</hi> for the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>man</hi> is a <hi>Devil,</hi> and ye worſhip that; thus you build your <hi>foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> thus <hi>God is good, and all is God,</hi> and we may do what we liſt; as we <hi>live</hi> ſo we <hi>dy;</hi> and come forth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170905:17"/>into other things as <hi>graſſe, Roots;</hi> who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived you? 'tis the <hi>Ly in your right hand,</hi> and ye will not know it, becauſe the <hi>knowledge</hi> is <hi>death</hi> to your preſent <hi>enjoyments.</hi> O that you would <hi>hear and return,</hi> why will you <hi>deſtroy</hi> your <hi>precious ſouls?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now your being is <hi>of,</hi> not <hi>in God,</hi> but <hi>by God,</hi> not <hi>from God,</hi> but <hi>to God;</hi> you ſhall be ſubject to his <hi>aiſpleaſure,</hi> you that will not <hi>obey,</hi> ſhall <hi>obey</hi> by force, for God is juſt, holy, and good; Now to let you know that that cloak of <hi>Antinomia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme</hi> is well wore, 'tis 1245 years old, it hath been turned by <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> and yet it is on again <hi>afreſh,</hi> and new trim'd, that it is better in <hi>ſhow,</hi> and fuller <hi>Napt</hi> then it was at <hi>first;</hi> for it took its being from a <hi>Clothier</hi> in <hi>Armenia,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Germany,</hi> then to <hi>France,</hi> now <hi>England</hi> ſwarms with Cloth of that colour (Of) will hold in that ſtate.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the cloſe of this point, it is this, that you are the <hi>name,</hi> and not the <hi>thing,</hi> and ye are both <hi>name</hi> and the thing; and that is two <hi>lyes</hi> in two <hi>ſtates:</hi> thus you are named <hi>Profeſſors of the Goſpel,</hi> that you have the <hi>name,</hi> and are not the <hi>thing,</hi> that is one <hi>Ly</hi> in that ſtate; the other is, you are the name <hi>Ante nomen,</hi> and ye are the <hi>thing</hi> and <hi>name:</hi> now there is two <hi>lyes</hi> in one <hi>ſtate,</hi> becauſe the <hi>name</hi> is a <hi>ly,</hi> and the <hi>thing</hi> a <hi>ly,</hi> and yet both the <hi>name</hi> and the <hi>thing</hi> hold the <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant intended;</hi> but it is a <hi>ly</hi> in the <hi>foundation,</hi> and then no <hi>name,</hi> or <hi>thing</hi> can be ſtated, but muſt be as the <hi>foundation</hi> is: ſo much for you <hi>Ante-no-men,</hi> or <hi>Ranters,</hi> all one in the <hi>root,</hi> though you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170905:18"/>
               <hi>branches</hi> look one <hi>divers</hi> from another, you are the <hi>ſame</hi> in your <hi>ſtructure</hi> or <hi>building.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> you <hi>rest</hi> my <hi>brethren accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fleſh,</hi> you <hi>reſt</hi> in your <hi>obſervation;</hi> now your <hi>obſervation</hi> to <hi>reſt</hi> upon is, to make that <hi>reſt unreſt</hi> to you, by <hi>reſting</hi> upon that <hi>reſt</hi> which is not <hi>true reſt,</hi> and by <hi>conſequence</hi> no <hi>reſt</hi> at all: God is your <hi>reſt,</hi> and no <hi>ceremony</hi> is <hi>reſt,</hi> but <hi>unreſt.</hi> Thus if your <hi>reſt</hi> be in and upon <hi>God,</hi> then you <hi>reſt</hi> in <hi>obeying his Commands:</hi> but <hi>Moſes</hi> my <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (I own him now) in what <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> ſtate I <hi>write,</hi> I <hi>know,</hi> but 'tis <hi>hid</hi> to you, he ſaid, if you obey the <hi>Commandments, which the Lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you, it ſhall go well with you; but if ye will not obey my commandment, then I will ſcatter you:</hi> Now my <hi>Brethren,</hi> I that have been <hi>ſcattered</hi> with you, am <hi>ſenſible</hi> of our <hi>eſtate.</hi> As the Lord hath ſhown me my <hi>Radax</hi> was <hi>Aaron, Moſes</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Lords <hi>Prieſt;</hi> then <hi>Zachariah</hi> was my <hi>Radax,</hi> whom they ſlew <hi>betwixt the Temple and the Altar;</hi> after this I was carried away with <hi>Jeconiah</hi> into <hi>Babylon</hi> in that <hi>ſeventy yeers capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,</hi> then I was <hi>Prieſt</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in <hi>Hoſha</hi> my <hi>Radax,</hi> and continued in the <hi>Prieſts Office</hi> till the ſecond <hi>Captivity,</hi> then I was carryed into <hi>Egypt</hi> by <hi>Pharaoh Necho,</hi> and returned with <hi>Zorobabel</hi> in the time of <hi>Salmanaſſer,</hi> not <hi>Jeconiah</hi> but <hi>Hoſai;</hi> but the <hi>Hebrew</hi> is <hi>tranſlated</hi> wrong in that <hi>ſtate,</hi> as I ſhall make appear when I come to <hi>unfold</hi> the <hi>patched Tranſlations, vilifying</hi> ſome <hi>Genealogies,</hi> and <hi>Deifying</hi> ſome, and ſome left quite <hi>out,</hi> that are <hi>extant</hi> in other <hi>Records</hi> in the <hi>Eaſtern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170905:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>as in <hi>Media, Perſia,</hi> and <hi>Egypt;</hi> then into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivity</hi> by <hi>Titus Veſpaſian,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Rome,</hi> from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>France</hi> in <hi>Charlemaigne,</hi> from that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent to <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>ſeventh,</hi> that was true Heit to <hi>Englands Crown</hi> before the <hi>conqueſt</hi> of <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Normandy,</hi> as from <hi>Saggus, Henegiſt,</hi> and <hi>Chropher,</hi> that is a <hi>proper word,</hi> and <hi>pertinent</hi> to the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in its proper tongue: yet beyond all this, now you will <hi>admire,</hi> and count it ſtrange, now the <hi>end</hi> will make the <hi>tractate declarative,</hi> aſſume of theſe things, let me add one I enjoy; though I was unlearned, all languages under heaven I had given me in ſeven days ſpace; this is a <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> in our days, not to take up your thoughts: thus, when God had a mighty work to do, did not he fit men with <hi>abilities,</hi> indued them with <hi>Power?</hi> Did not the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> at being <hi>called,</hi> ſpeak with <hi>new Tongues?</hi> now ye <hi>Prieſts</hi> my <hi>Brethren,</hi> if you <hi>Prieſts,</hi> I much more; for unto me is this <hi>grace given,</hi> that I ſhould <hi>unſeal</hi> the hidden <hi>depth</hi> of <hi>depths</hi> in all <hi>myſteries</hi> and all <hi>knowledge:</hi> but I am a <hi>child</hi> as yet, but with my <hi>weakneſs</hi> I ſhall be <hi>wiſe, through him that hath loved me with everlaſting love:</hi> Now ye <hi>Jewes,</hi> my <hi>Brethren,</hi> for our diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience the Lord hath caſt us out of our <hi>inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance,</hi> and our <hi>glory</hi> lies in the <hi>duſt,</hi> and poor <hi>Sion,</hi> for whom my <hi>Soul</hi> is pained even to <hi>death</hi> for her <hi>deliverance.</hi> O God remember <hi>Sion</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that thou haſt <hi>choſen,</hi> Remember ſhe, O Lord, is <hi>deſolate,</hi> and her children in <hi>poverty,</hi> and <hi>captivity, confound</hi> them that wiſh her <hi>hurt;</hi> and O Lord, <hi>bleſs</hi> them that wiſh her <hi>welfare</hi> to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170905:19"/>
               <hi>reſtoration.</hi> O it had been better <hi>we had not known,</hi> then that <hi>we ſhould not enjoy:</hi> O God, the <hi>Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren are come to the birth, and there is no ſtrength to bring forth; Our eyes are unto thee, O God, and in thee, and from thee, and by thee ſhall we be reſtored:</hi> O all ye people, behold <hi>whoſe ſorrow is like our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> we have been in <hi>captivity</hi> ſo many hundred years, and all <hi>rule</hi> over us, and <hi>oppreſs</hi> us, what was the cauſe of this <hi>grievous ſtroke?</hi> it was <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience:</hi> You <hi>diſobedient</hi> know God is <hi>juſt,</hi> if he <hi>caſt</hi> us off, how expect you to <hi>ſtand?</hi> Look, <hi>ſin</hi> is one and the <hi>ſame,</hi> now God is making <hi>inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> for <hi>bloud,</hi> this I know; what the <hi>effect</hi> will be I know not; but thus God will <hi>repay</hi> in <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>ſury:</hi> I ſee a <hi>black Skie,</hi> where that <hi>Meteor</hi> will <hi>diſſolve</hi> it ſelf into the <hi>terreſtial Orbs,</hi> I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine; nay, I know <hi>fall</hi> it will with <hi>violence</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume</hi> the lifted up in pride; but our <hi>deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> is from God alone: now <hi>Brethren,</hi> know we and our <hi>Fathers</hi> have done <hi>wickedly,</hi> and <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed</hi> the holy <hi>Covenant:</hi> now what is the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi> 'tis <hi>Love,</hi> and for want of <hi>Love</hi> hath this <hi>great evil</hi> come upon us, as we may with ſad <hi>hearts,</hi> and ſorrowfull <hi>ſpirits</hi> ſet to our <hi>ſeals;</hi> but I look fully to ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> reſtored, <hi>re-edified;</hi> for God cauſes not this <hi>Learning</hi> to come forth to be <hi>preached</hi> in another World: <hi>Wo unto the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth, for a fire is a kindling, and the flame will not be quenched, till it effect its end:</hi> for days of <hi>ſorrow</hi> and <hi>mourning</hi> is at hand. Now <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> writes, and as it is tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſaying, <hi>The time is at hand,</hi> how many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170905:19"/>years was it wrote, that word is Truth in his <hi>Radax,</hi> for it is the preſent tenſe <hi>ſtated,</hi> and holds <hi>ever</hi> and all ages, and times, for at hand is: they looked for its <hi>appearance,</hi> and it <hi>hung,</hi> and doth <hi>hang,</hi> like a <hi>Commet</hi> in the Air, <hi>attracting</hi> the Eye of all that paſs, that <hi>Species</hi> being a Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word to them: now this word <hi>Euſebean</hi> is the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Greek word, or radical expreſſion of ſome event dangerous in its <hi>adherents</hi> or <hi>dependants,</hi> as to ſay, the deſtruction of this or that may be, nay, will be, the deſtruction of this or that: ſo <hi>Eroclidon</hi> is the ſame in effect both Greek Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds from the Hebrew radiaſes, holding the ſame <hi>influ;</hi> but <hi>Euſabean</hi> is the proper Word, as thus, 'tis Radaxed thus <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Now <hi>Eroclidon</hi> is thus <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> yet here is the oddes, the one admits no <hi>adjunct,</hi> and the other doth in its <hi>defendant</hi> ittere, there it admits a <hi>connection,</hi> and may be impeaded there, and the T Y leſſened, which <hi>Euſabean</hi> cannot, becauſe 'tis barred in <hi>Sambah,</hi> or <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech,</hi> being the full <hi>ſignificant</hi> in the <hi>intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi> ſtate ſtated: But to come to the <hi>Divine</hi> Story, which is <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>fleſh, ſeen of men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived up to glory:</hi> here is in this the whole <hi>inklu</hi> of the whole <hi>Story,</hi> what <hi>Chriſt</hi> was he is, now what he is, he was, and ever the ſame, no <hi>leſs</hi> he <hi>was,</hi> he <hi>is,</hi> and to come, the Father, Father, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers glory, he is not <hi>dead</hi> but <hi>riſen,</hi> a reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on daily, hourly, when he was in the <hi>grave,</hi> where
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170905:20"/>vvas the life of the <hi>Creation, ſem in loco aſaphet, El doni aberet in loco tem deni aharet, ad me inter pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati alvah in ſabat,</hi> this I engliſh not, <hi>non quia pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavi: ſed,</hi> but the people cannot bear it, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds the vveak, &amp; ſhakes the ſtrong; <hi>ſed ſum in loco olva in latinam ad re quia non habuit, ſe in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſalvah heni tenrei vele nec amico oli bene dere ad me allah ſola malta alſial ad me mecavi <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> plecavi ad me inſerta alvah ola denet amo oli benede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret lama abſane in ſo operati addit verat alma,</hi> the divine Myſtery is a ſealed Book many times to him that is <hi>Pon-Man,</hi> vvhen I <hi>write,</hi> I have no <hi>knowledge,</hi> neither <hi>behind</hi> nor <hi>before,</hi> but the vvord that comes, I haſte to bee rid of, for 'tis not like vvriting a <hi>Letter,</hi> and thoughts hovv to <hi>contrive,</hi> but it is it <hi>ſelf,</hi> expreſſing it <hi>ſelf,</hi> through this <hi>vail</hi> of <hi>fleſh:</hi> Novv to give the <hi>ſtate,</hi> and take the <hi>ſtate,</hi> I vvill <hi>confound</hi> the vvhole <hi>Earth,</hi> not I, but the <hi>Light</hi> in me, to bring <hi>variety</hi> into <hi>unity,</hi> and <hi>unity</hi> again into pure <hi>variety:</hi> Novv the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Viſion</hi> of S. <hi>John,</hi> that <hi>word</hi> is not vvell <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> in our <hi>dayes,</hi> the thing intended is <hi>truth,</hi> then it may plead <hi>priviledge</hi> for the <hi>ſame,</hi> but his <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> are various in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and in <hi>tranſlating</hi> they have made them more <hi>various</hi> and <hi>doubtfull,</hi> as in this place. The <hi>Godhead bodily,</hi> and divers ſuch <hi>metamorphos'd</hi> things, I cannot tell vvhere to begin, but take a <hi>ſay</hi> to ſhevv the <hi>whole:</hi> Novv I deſire to knovv vvhat is meant by the <hi>Godhead bodily,</hi> from vvhence comes this <hi>Monſter,</hi> the <hi>Godhead bodily</hi> is abſolute <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> the Text
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170905:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>ought to have been rendered <hi>Evi en ſanet arri beneal alter in ago aſalet mem,</hi> the Engliſh thus, the <hi>Deity</hi> is not confin'd, nor cannot be <hi>limitted,</hi> then hovv can it be ſaid to dvvell <hi>boaily,</hi> vvhen it is in <hi>all bodies</hi> at once, and one <hi>time,</hi> and alvvayes the <hi>ſame,</hi> and yet not <hi>bodied?</hi> The <hi>Deity</hi> hath no <hi>body,</hi> 'tis <hi>ſpirit,</hi> any 'tis <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>life</hi> is not <hi>body; Doctors</hi> what ſay you? this calls for your <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> the body is a body when life is gone, and <hi>life</hi> is <hi>life,</hi> the body nothing: Now life is the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> in <hi>Man,</hi> and not <hi>Man,</hi> nor of <hi>Man,</hi> nor by <hi>Man,</hi> yet the <hi>life</hi> of the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> this is a <hi>glimpſe</hi> of the <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> or <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi> or <hi>Adoniel,</hi> or <hi>Aloah,</hi> or <hi>L,</hi> or <hi>Jah,</hi> or God the ſame all, all the ſame, and but one <hi>Name,</hi> One thing tendered by theſe <hi>diſtincts:</hi> Now the next, <hi>He was born of the Virgin Mary,</hi> how comes this from the Greek <hi>Abadoniſme?</hi> how can he that created all, and is all, be <hi>humanity,</hi> and born of a <hi>woman?</hi> that <hi>woman</hi> intended in that <hi>ſtate,</hi> is not <hi>known</hi> in that <hi>ſtate,</hi> let me tell you that <hi>woman</hi> is <hi>Hevah,</hi> that is, the <hi>Weak Creation</hi> in <hi>Man,</hi> and all things, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, the whole <hi>Creation groans to be delivered,</hi> the very <hi>Beaſts</hi> groan for a <hi>deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> with us: <hi>A Virgin ſhall conceive,</hi> the Text ſaith, but 'tis a <hi>Virgin</hi> ſhall bring <hi>forth</hi> her <hi>firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Son,</hi> what is this? 'tis the <hi>birth</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> That <hi>(of)</hi> bears a right ſtate there; now I am forced for your <hi>underſtanding</hi> to write <hi>(of)</hi> but the <hi>intendant</hi> is contrary in me: Now what is meant by the <hi>Virgin</hi> and her Son? <hi>In ſentarie Octabris in ſe ſola ad me,</hi> they ſhall call his name <hi>Emanuel,</hi> that is,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170905:21"/>
               <hi>A Saviour,</hi> I grant all this; <hi>the ſeed of the woman ſhall break his head, and he ſhall bruiſe her heel,</hi> what is this? <hi>alluſive</hi> to the ſame <hi>ſtate,</hi> yet nothing to the Greek rendered Tranſlation, <hi>To us a Child is horn, to us a Son is given,</hi> I deny the <hi>Minor,</hi> and grant the <hi>Major,</hi> this is a ſtrange ſtate, when the <hi>Major</hi> includes the <hi>Minor,</hi> moſt times thus, I open, <hi>ſed pars &amp; partis in partis in ſepe locat,</hi> thus, A Child is born is granted, but not the Songi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, A Child is the infant birth in the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of our <hi>ſpirit,</hi> which is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or Gods <hi>ſpirit,</hi> or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> or <hi>anointing,</hi> that is, the <hi>Virgin ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> but the word is A <hi>Virgin</hi> ſhall bring <hi>forth</hi> a <hi>Child,</hi> which Child is <hi>Love. To us a ſon is given,</hi> how? becauſe he cannot be parted from <hi>himſelf,</hi> the <hi>Trine</hi> muſt ceaſe operation, then no <hi>Deity,</hi> thus God doth deliver us by the <hi>influes</hi> of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo doth awaken us to the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of the <hi>juſt,</hi> made <hi>perfect</hi> by his <hi>Reſurrection</hi> in us, is not the <hi>Child</hi> the <hi>Minor?</hi> no, 'tis the <hi>Major,</hi> and 'tis all, for a <hi>child</hi> is a <hi>ſon,</hi> and a <hi>child,</hi> and the <hi>child</hi> ſtated in that ſtate includes the <hi>ſon,</hi> ſo the <hi>ſon</hi> is but <hi>name,</hi> the ſubſtance being in <hi>name</hi> and thing, cited in the ſame ſtate, now the <hi>Major</hi> and <hi>Minor</hi> are both one &amp; the ſame, no one or other, but both one and other the ſame, <hi>he was anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above his fellows,</hi> what is that? He received a fuller meaſure then ever any did, or ſhall do, how was that? God <hi>gave it to him not by meaſure,</hi> this is a great <hi>myſtery</hi> that is, not known to this day, the <hi>Apostles</hi> knew it not, as I am able to make <hi>manifeſt.</hi> Now know the Spirit is not <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170905:21"/>but all beyond <hi>meaſure</hi> or <hi>comprehenſion,</hi> this <hi>reaches</hi> not yet, <hi>God</hi> is <hi>God, Chriſt</hi> is God, the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> is God, and God every where acting forth as he <hi>pleaſes:</hi> Now not that the <hi>body of Chriſt</hi> was more, but that <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> did reveal the <hi>light</hi> of, nay <hi>himſelf,</hi> through that <hi>vail,</hi> more then any to that <hi>day:</hi> Now God is <hi>(A)</hi> nay, the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and doth declare himſelf wondrous <hi>wayes,</hi> the whole <hi>Creation</hi> is but his <hi>unfoldings</hi> of <hi>himſelf,</hi> in his <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties,</hi> and his <hi>clothing</hi> himſelf in the <hi>creative</hi> in their <hi>creatived</hi> eſtate: Now afterward I ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold the <hi>humanity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in ſome other place or book, but 'tis not pertinent. Now I can ſay what you ſay, and you underſtand not your <hi>ſelves,</hi> nor the intended myſtery.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the Greek tongue, that is our eſſential eſſence, 'tis the <hi>Abadon,</hi> that Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaw, that Deſtroyer that roſe out of the bottomleſſe pit, that is, <hi>the heart of Man,</hi> for your Philoſophers and Stoicks were very curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in new coyning new words, and nice <hi>Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmes,</hi> whileſt they loſt their old ſtamp, <hi>for the wiſdom of man is enmity againſt God</hi> (as <hi>Paul</hi> well ſaid) but that would not bar them, for invading and intrenching on, and into the truth to make an in-let to their coyned invention and nicety, in full, they turned their glory into ſhame, for they have vilified the truth, by making it to bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter uy their in-weaved Ly into the truth named. Now here comes the birth or generation of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in their forged Dipthongs, As <hi>ae, ei, oa, au, el, uieii, &amp;c.</hi> Of this ſort is to ſound two in one,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170905:22"/>one in three, five in one, and from this invention came the <hi>Now Logick,</hi> to prove that that is not to be by rule and conſequence, and to prove that that is not to be, to be by the ſame rule or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, this is <hi>Logick;</hi> but now 'tis high Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity amongſt us called, but call is a ly, and ſo is that bolſtering Divinity: Now know I will not read any, nor look on any books of Hebrew, Greek, or Latine, or read any Father: Now I cannot work at all times, but when the <hi>Spirit</hi> will, I need no Authours, for a thouſand or five thouſand years, I can find Authours. What is hid from light it ſelf, remember I ſaid, I am but the Pen in the <hi>Spirit's</hi> hand, ſo as to ſay, I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that is, <hi>Man:</hi> and mans, that is, at mans command to act when he will, by that character you may know it, that it hath its own ſtamp up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, now 'tis not ſo with me, ſometime an hour one day, two dayes, three dayes at this time: Now I have been deſired to ſpeak to baptiſm, and this Text ſtated, <hi>Go and teach all Nations, and baptize them in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> to which Text I deny the very being in Baptiſm named in his eſſence, that Text was wrote in Hebrew, onely a <hi>collateral</hi> Word was Greek, to leſſen the Ty in the ſtate ſtated by S. <hi>Mark:</hi> the <hi>Radaxes</hi> in that Text is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there is the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daxes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hebraically cited, there is but one impeade in the whole ſtate, which will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170905:22"/>admit of any liquid ſubſtance; the impead is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>caf,</hi> Now then you take <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaded,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>TY</hi> at his <hi>ſoal,</hi> that is a <hi>proper-word,</hi> and <hi>radically</hi> expreſſed; to let you know 'tis <hi>Prin</hi> that is <hi>Arabaically</hi> wrote, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let the Greek <hi>Kion</hi> in, to leſſen the ſtrength of the tyed <hi>TY,</hi> to make an harmonious compoſure or <hi>aſſent</hi> in <hi>conſent,</hi> radically <hi>examplifying:</hi> Now the <hi>ſimblim</hi> or word <hi>derived</hi> from his <hi>Radax,</hi> is <hi>Thufali ol obenen in ſe okorari abbah abſaet;</hi> the <hi>derivaſi</hi> is in Engliſh, <hi>Go teach the people my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> or <hi>knowledge of me:</hi> Where is there any bottom for <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to ſtand in this Text? but it is tranſlated ſo, and a cuſtome; Doth <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> ſtand on <hi>Cuſtome?</hi> no; <hi>Learning</hi> doth ſtand on <hi>custome,</hi> for <hi>Learning</hi> is a <hi>Ly,</hi> and ſo a <hi>cuſtom,</hi> ſo a <hi>cuſtome</hi> to <hi>Ly</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> both; we having <hi>Truth,</hi> need not go to ſee what another <hi>hath ſaid</hi> or <hi>doth ſay,</hi> for <hi>truth</hi> is the <hi>thing</hi> in query, a <hi>ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> and <hi>nothing; John</hi> baptiſed in <hi>Enon,</hi> and who? <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women, Believers;</hi> what is this to <hi>Infants baptiſm?</hi> nothing for you: well, to that I anſwer, if <hi>all</hi> then, but not a <hi>reſt</hi> to <hi>reſt</hi> on, but being in <hi>faith</hi> in <hi>obedience</hi> to that, if it be moved <hi>within,</hi> it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not; but the <hi>ſtate now</hi> and <hi>then</hi> was <hi>different,</hi> and will admit of no <hi>compoſure;</hi> for theirs was in the <hi>womb,</hi> ours at the <hi>laſt breath:</hi> I write <hi>ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> but it will be <hi>true,</hi> for the <hi>Lord</hi> of the <hi>Vinyard</hi> is coming to call his ſervants to <hi>account</hi> for the <hi>Talent</hi> delivered, and not being <hi>faithful</hi> in the <hi>thing,</hi> only holding a <hi>Name,</hi> and that for the <hi>cloak</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170905:23"/>to <hi>eflect</hi> an other <hi>end;</hi> he condemned this, <hi>I know he will give his Vinyard to another people;</hi> and this is the <hi>Myſtery</hi> opened in that <hi>Parable:</hi> now what <hi>availed</hi> the <hi>Baptiſed</hi> at <hi>mans eſtate?</hi> In <hi>Johns</hi> time they were <hi>Believers,</hi> and to <hi>Believe,</hi> is <hi>Obedience</hi> in <hi>Love,</hi> and that is <hi>Lite Eternal;</hi> why they muſt be <hi>Believers,</hi> elſe <hi>non baptizatus, in re locat ad me nullos in rem pacuiſſe ſed volemus in tertia loca ad meam in trinas perſonas aluat adoramus in pacuiſse velvat:</hi> The Engliſh, <hi>Not baptiſed becauſe they did not believe, but baptiſed becauſe they did believe</hi> Now then, they had not ſuch a meaſure of <hi>head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learning,</hi> nor <hi>tongue equivocations,</hi> but in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of their <hi>ſpirits</hi> ſubmitted to the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand:</hi> Know a Believer muſt be an <hi>innocent harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe</hi> man. Now know I can read a <hi>negative deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy</hi> from an <hi>Affirmative ſtate</hi> out from the ſame <hi>Radaxes,</hi> by the <hi>collateral conjunct,</hi> and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct:</hi> now you admire <hi>I render</hi> not the <hi>Word</hi> as <hi>you</hi> do; thus every <hi>Latine</hi> Word holding the ſame <hi>ſignification,</hi> thus I ſhow you in two words <hi>(ſed, but,)</hi> this is quite another thing, in another thing <hi>ſtated, (ſi, if,)</hi> 'tis <hi>glory</hi> in another <hi>ſtate,</hi> as <hi>treas perſonas, three perſons;</hi> you ſee it is not <hi>named</hi> at all, not becauſe I <hi>know not</hi> as you <hi>know,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I <hi>know</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> you have the learned <hi>Ly,</hi> and an <hi>old one,</hi> now I can <hi>influ</hi> in the leaſt <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound,</hi> as <hi>ſe,</hi> or <hi>impeade</hi> or <hi>leſſen</hi> the <hi>TY,</hi> in <hi>rendring</hi> the <hi>ſtate ſtated:</hi> But now to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> thus, <hi>they were baptiſed,</hi> to what? to <hi>Johns Baptiſme,</hi> nay, to <hi>believe on him that ſhould come after;</hi> who was that? that was <hi>Chriſt, Life, Jehovah, Jah;</hi> this is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170905:23"/>but <hi>name,</hi> and cannot confer the <hi>thing;</hi> the <hi>thing</hi> is it ſelf, and the <hi>name</hi> is let down to <hi>hint</hi> us of the <hi>thing;</hi> as that Text rendred, <hi>There is no name given under heaven, that we muſt be ſaved by, but the name Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> I ſay it is <hi>falſe tranſlated</hi> in the <hi>intendant in</hi> the <hi>Spirit (Of the Spirit)</hi> I ſpeak <hi>your</hi> word <hi>(of)</hi> the true meaning of the <hi>Spirit</hi> is, that they ſhould <hi>believe</hi> in God, <hi>believe</hi> in him that <hi>ſent</hi> me? Who was that? The <hi>All of all things,</hi> ſo it is <hi>things</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> reſts on, and not <hi>names;</hi> for the <hi>name</hi> is not <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>thing,</hi> but the <hi>thing</hi> is the material <hi>in</hi> all, <hi>of</hi> all, and <hi>by</hi> all that <hi>by</hi> it gave a <hi>being</hi> to all, therefore is <hi>all,</hi> to that <hi>all</hi> be glory, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In truth <hi>Baptiſme</hi> was a <hi>ſeal</hi> of <hi>Fellowſhip,</hi> and no more, and that is all it is, deifie it as you pleaſe, not that a man is <hi>better</hi> or <hi>worſe</hi> for it, or <hi>without</hi> it; <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Circumciſion or uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion availeth not,</hi> but <hi>obedience</hi> in <hi>love</hi> is the <hi>birth</hi> of God: To that <hi>Child</hi> the <hi>reward</hi> of <hi>glory</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and no <hi>other thing:</hi> To be in <hi>love,</hi> is to be in <hi>light;</hi> to be in <hi>light,</hi> is to be in <hi>God, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polycarpus</hi> in his writings he wrote <hi>hierogliphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally,</hi> and ye read it <hi>literally;</hi> How ſay you, can we do otherwiſe? no, 'tis true, he wrote by <hi>light,</hi> and ye read with <hi>ſpectacles</hi> of your <hi>own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> ſo you ſee not his <hi>ſcope:</hi> He was an <hi>Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> indeed, but he was <hi>Divine</hi> as well as <hi>Humane,</hi> as his <hi>Citations</hi> will manifeſt (that were his) but I deny you to have his words, for they were <hi>preſt</hi> out when your <hi>Fathers</hi> fell a <hi>Printing;</hi> for ye <hi>printed out</hi> the <hi>true print,</hi> and put a <hi>baſe ſtamp</hi> of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170905:24"/>your <hi>own</hi> on, not in <hi>him</hi> alone, but in <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>Jerome,</hi> and all the reſt. Now you will ſay, this man is well <hi>learned,</hi> I ſay in <hi>knowledge,</hi> for ſay you, <hi>he knows the Fathers:</hi> To that I anſwer, I know the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and can cite <hi>Authors,</hi> and their <hi>word</hi> in any tongue under heaven, yet never <hi>ſaw,</hi> nor <hi>read</hi> book in my life of them, nor any one of them. Now you <hi>admire;</hi> to take off that <hi>admiration,</hi> I anſwer this, What is hid from the <hi>light</hi> it ſelf? Know but that ſhort <hi>ſtate</hi> truly, and <hi>admiration</hi> is <hi>gone:</hi> 'Tis for want of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ye admire. <hi>Non ſum in Re ex hock ad meam in ſola mem derata alvah:</hi> I am not in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to my own alone, but to you are theſe high things ſent to <hi>enlighten</hi> you. Now <hi>light</hi> is come to this poor wearied <hi>Nation,</hi> and from <hi>her</hi> the <hi>Son of Righteouſneſſe ſhall ariſe</hi> in full luſter to the whole earth; nay the <hi>Declarative</hi> of Truth from the <hi>Radax</hi> it ſelf, but for the ſake of the <hi>caſt</hi> off <hi>Jewes,</hi> as you ſay, but <hi>Ariſe</hi> and <hi>ſhine,</hi> for thy <hi>time</hi> is <hi>come,</hi> thou poor <hi>Shulamite,</hi> thy God will adorn thee with glorious Majeſty, as in thy <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin</hi> dayes, when thou waſt the <hi>beautiful Queen,</hi> and <hi>Princeſſe</hi> of the <hi>Provinces,</hi> when thy <hi>beauty</hi> was <hi>freſh</hi> and <hi>delightful,</hi> and thy <hi>glory</hi> did atract the hearts and eyes of the whole <hi>Nations,</hi> when thou waſt <hi>chaſt</hi> and <hi>unſpotted;</hi> but thou haſt fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from thy <hi>firſt love:</hi> for what end? that thy <hi>fall</hi> might bring in others, and a far more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>reſurrection</hi> to thy ſelf, and enlighten the <hi>whole Earth</hi> with thee: <hi>They ſhall come from far to worſhip in Jeruſalem</hi> temporal: for that <hi>ſtate</hi> of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170905:24"/>
               <hi>coming</hi> can hold no other ſenſe but Men and Women, <hi>to the Houſe of the Lord:</hi> There is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Mule,</hi> nor <hi>ſwift Beaſts</hi> in the <hi>Heavenly Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem: I Theaurau John ſaw and beheld, but that ſtate to expreſs, I am taken with the inraviſhment:</hi> My Spirit will not keep center'd in my body, for the out reachings after that glory.</p>
            <p>O, O, O, For O it is <hi>Devicie Devinam in Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagorum in Evangelorum in ſe voſe non hominem ſed Evangelieficalius in re, ex re, id re negat, O vale, O vale, O vale ſed enim tempus quia reſurreckſit ad ſe in meam oculous ad celum ſatiatam ad me non locat verbus ſed Devinam eſt, eſt, eſt,</hi> O no other Heaven I could deſire, ſo I mightenjoy but this rapture I am in at this Writing: <hi>O terra, O Terra, O Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Abballa ad me ſed eſtemat te Skubulo oreat in ſe:</hi> Now to come into Hell, which is this Earthly priſon, oh how have I loſt my enjoyment in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Divine things? O that there were no place but that: This is <hi>errour, peccavi</hi> in this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſee the <hi>ſtate ſtated</hi> by the <hi>Eternal Being enim tempus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come to the <hi>dry bones,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> are inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that <hi>myſterious alluſe</hi> for are they not now at this day <hi>bones</hi> without <hi>fleſh</hi> &amp; <hi>ſcaterd</hi> th' earth <hi>over?</hi> Have they not had the <hi>evil Vials</hi> of <hi>wrath</hi> poured on them? and ſhal not the <hi>good</hi> promiſed be <hi>enjoyed</hi> by them? ſurely God is juſt. Ye <hi>Gentiles</hi> love the <hi>Jewes;</hi> my <hi>Brethren,</hi> ye <hi>Jewes,</hi> love the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> do but this throughly, and then nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jew,</hi> nor <hi>Gentile,</hi> nor <hi>Gentile,</hi> neither <hi>Jew,</hi> but both <hi>one</hi> in the <hi>Unity</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> which is <hi>one
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170905:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>Spirit,</hi> and both <hi>one</hi> in the <hi>Father;</hi> this is the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</hi> from <hi>death</hi> to <hi>life. Love, love</hi> is <hi>God, God</hi> is <hi>Mercy,</hi> this <hi>Mercy</hi> is tendred to all: The <hi>Jew</hi> a <hi>name,</hi> the <hi>Gentile</hi> a <hi>name,</hi> but <hi>love</hi> is that that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names both, grafting it ſelf into <hi>both,</hi> to bring <hi>both</hi> into it, and then is written this <hi>new Name that no man knoweth, but he that hath received it,</hi> which is <hi>Love:</hi> My name is <hi>John,</hi> the <hi>ſignificant</hi> is, the <hi>Dove;</hi> now the <hi>nature</hi> of a <hi>Dove</hi> is <hi>Loving alone; alone</hi> is <hi>one,</hi> that <hi>one</hi> is <hi>God:</hi> The <hi>Dove</hi> brought an <hi>Olive leaf</hi> in her mouth, as the <hi>Story</hi> ſaith, what is the thing <hi>intendant</hi> in that <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliphyck,</hi> for an <hi>Hierogliphick</hi> is an Embleme of ſomwhat more than is expreſt in that ſemblance, that ſemblance cited is to <hi>alluſe</hi> to ſomewhat more ſignificant: <hi>F</hi> is <hi>imperfect,</hi> and to be <hi>layd by</hi> when I <hi>write</hi> the <hi>Divine Myſtery;</hi> the <hi>alluſe</hi> in the <hi>Dove</hi> and her <hi>leaf,</hi> was not I think it was ſo, but I know it is ſo: <hi>Think</hi> is a <hi>ly; Truth</hi> it ſelf admits no <hi>thoughts,</hi> the <hi>Dove</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> his name was <hi>Holah,</hi> that ſignifies <hi>highly beloved;</hi> now where God <hi>loves,</hi> it is <hi>perfection,</hi> and his <hi>perfection</hi> is not ſpelt <hi>by</hi> or <hi>with</hi> a <hi>falſe Name:</hi> Can <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelf <hi>cite</hi> falſe names to <hi>illuſtrate</hi> the Truth? no you are <hi>deceived;</hi> now <hi>Noah</hi> is derived from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Holah</hi> is derived from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there is <hi>perfection</hi> in the laſt, and <hi>imperfection</hi> in the firſt; the <hi>TI</hi> in <hi>R Hettau</hi> is imperfect, now the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> them two you cannot ſpell, becauſe it is <hi>perfection,</hi> they will bear it in one
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170905:25"/>and in both, as thus <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, <hi>Man in his perfect eſtate,</hi> or <hi>Man refined by God to himſelf:</hi> this is worth the <hi>deepest Judgements</hi> looking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to and upon: Now the <hi>Dove</hi> that then was <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphick,</hi> was the <hi>ſemblance</hi> of God <hi>tendring</hi> nay <hi>giving</hi> himſelf to the people; the <hi>leaf</hi> was the <hi>peace</hi> that the <hi>Man-hood</hi> had deſtroyed, yet he would reſtore it in <hi>himſelf;</hi> for God made us <hi>ſtrong,</hi> we became <hi>weak;</hi> he cauſes a <hi>reſurrection</hi> in us, that is, himſelf <hi>ariſing</hi> and <hi>ſubjecting</hi> all things in us to <hi>love,</hi> and that <hi>love</hi> is God, and that <hi>love</hi> begot us at <hi>firſt,</hi> and <hi>reſtores</hi> us in the <hi>ſecond,</hi> and brings us into the <hi>thira Perſon</hi> in the <hi>Trine.</hi> Now that word <hi>Trine</hi> is ſomwhat ſtrange, but it is the <hi>firſt, ſecond,</hi> and <hi>third ſtate,</hi> ▿ of the <hi>Deity,</hi> there is the <hi>Trine</hi> in the Humanity, and the <hi>Trine</hi> is in, nay, is the whole <hi>creatived Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Product,</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>Triplicity,</hi> or <hi>three Perſons</hi> in the the <hi>Trinity:</hi> Now to know theſe truly, is <hi>life eternal,</hi> for true knowledge is to be in the <hi>Trine,</hi> or elſe not <hi>knowledge,</hi> but <hi>fooliſh learning.</hi> Now know, <hi>knowledge</hi> I honour, Learning that is know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or elſe I ſhould diſhonour God himſelf, that is knowledge and learning the heighth, and for <hi>teaching</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> I honour, and <hi>fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> one with another I honour, but how far? for knowledge that is learning it teaches, and them teachings is actual diſtributing <hi>love,</hi> the fruit is in its effects; now this is Truth, now
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170905:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>teaching as we teach, for to teach men to ſet up our ſelves, is teaching without knowledge, which teaching is a <hi>Ly,</hi> and not the <hi>thing;</hi> for mind, moſt of our Teachers teaches us <hi>themſelves,</hi> and not God, or teach us to themſelves from God: I do not ſay nor intend all, neither would I have them that are not to claim to them by this a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge where it is not intended, for know you, I know you to be a ſubtile generation, ye <hi>Prieſts,</hi> my <hi>Brethren,</hi> I acknowledge ye to be my <hi>brethren</hi> that be in the <hi>being,</hi> that's <hi>love,</hi> hold one more, that is love that declares it ſelf by compaſſionate <hi>diſtributives, tives, tives.</hi> There is in <hi>three</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: now I read <hi>Hebrew</hi> to many, and ye are but eſſenſed men, but I will give you a radical expreſſion that is in <hi>James</hi> his Epiſtle; <hi>He that ſees his brother in need, and relieves him not, how doth the love of God dwell in that man? that man is a ly, his Religion is vain.</hi> What a net full of Prieſts and people catched at one pull? Many of theſe pulls will leave but few, that I ſhall ſee cleerly, that <hi>many are called,</hi> and call, <hi>but few are choſen:</hi> Thus for teaching, and they themſelves in the being: Theſe are they that <hi>cauſe the way of Truth to be evil ſpoken of,</hi> but it is in an evil way, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and teachers in that good way; know, a good way cannot be taught, it is it ſelf, and teaches all; <hi>I am the way,</hi> He is that, why? <hi>it is Truth, Way, and Life.</hi> Now the learned muſt be condemned, for learning them, they teach the leſſon; and the Prieſt blamed, and the people not excuſed; for know O man, within thee is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170905:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>that that doth condemn thee; not for that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith of thee, but for that thou doſt thy ſelf: let me tell thee, that if thy knowledge were to be got in and by another, God could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thy ſelf; for, thou haſt a knowledge what to do, nay ought to do, and not for doing that that thou knoweſt and oughteſt to do, for that comes thy juſt condemnation; ſo it will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe thee to ſay, ſuch a one taught me, no, no, thy ſelf condemneſt thy ſelf, Witneſs, Judge, Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution is in and within thy ſelf: Teaching, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and Fellowſhip, is a three-fold cord, have one of them in truth, ye have all, they are inſeperable companions; it is unions unity in its own variety, it is the Deity it ſelf: now to this I add this <hi>motto, To be in God, is to act in love, and he that is not in love, is not in God, neither hath known him:</hi> now know once more, I can ſpeak truth, if my ſelf be <hi>radaxed</hi> in the truth, but I cannot confer truth to another; take heed you do not make an Idol of dependant hearing, more doing will be more anſwerable to our profeſſion, and leſs hearing; yet it is cleer moſt of us never heard in our lives, for actions are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratives whether we have heard or not: you ſay ſuch a man or woman is ſuch a mans hearer, or hears of ſuch a Miniſter, if he a Miniſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, thou diſhonoureſt him, and the Goſpel, as ye ſay, and thy actings make him and it a <hi>Ly,</hi> for God who is light and truth, thou ſetteſt up a a truth contrary, and not that that he delivers: Actions is true declaratives of that that is, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170905:27"/>that that is not, for <hi>if ye act righteouſneſs, then are ye the children of light, or elſe ye have not ſeen nor known light:</hi> now you leaders the Prieſts, they are turned Jewes, for ſay you, the Jewes were valiant men, and the Prieſts moſt noble and valiant in Wars, as the Stories record: if the Prieſt Jew, the people Jewiſh; why then the Jew and the Gentile in this ſtate are one; 'tis granted, 'tis truth in this ſtate, for he that is in darkneſs, be he Jew or Gentile, in that ſtate they be one, and the whole of the Creation is but one with them, for there is but light and darkneſs in the whole earth: now to prove the Prieſts to be Jews, then they are my brethren, then brethren ought <hi>to bear one with another:</hi> now my brethren, that ſtate you cannot deny me in Creation, and in Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I am <hi>Reuben,</hi> &amp; though he loſt his birth-right in <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſtory, yet he ſhould recover at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, and firſt in the <hi>trine</hi> in that revolution, which the world cannot hinder; here is more couched in this ſtate, then all men on earth can reach out, nor ſhall not, till time cauſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; but let me ſpeak, <hi>Ruben</hi> holds his Genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy cleer in preheminence, for <hi>a daughter of</hi> Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben, <hi>what</hi> Tribe <hi>ſhe matcht into, the</hi> Tribe <hi>lost the name till the fourth deſcent, the man was named</hi> Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben <hi>in Genealogie; and if a man took a Widdow of the</hi> Rubenite, <hi>his children by that woman were ever</hi> Rubenites, <hi>be of what</hi> Tribe <hi>ſoever.</hi> Now <hi>Judah</hi> held thus, <hi>that if a man of another</hi> Tribe <hi>took a wife of</hi> Judah, <hi>the man lost not his name, but the woman was reckoned of</hi> Judah <hi>till the fourth Genealogie or
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170905:27"/>deſcent, then the whole Iſſue fell to the</hi> Tribe <hi>the man was on, and remained ſo for ever.</hi> Know by this, I am as I have declared, <hi>Recordat de tredeſem tribas de Jewes: Recorder of the thirteen tribes of the Jewes.</hi> So now, to take my place by my Genealogie, ye Prieſts my brethren, if ye be, yet the ſtate is ſure in the ſtate of Creation, as afore cited, now I write to you I muſt come cloſe, for you are quick eyed, but ſlow paced <hi>in veras;</hi> now I ſtate this ſtate, I am neerer a Gentile in practiſe than you, for I act in love, <hi>I</hi> plead for love, <hi>I</hi> plead for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation by love; this is a declarative of truth in me to all; <hi>exce meam action is in ſe in veras ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritat as. I</hi> write it full bard in <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
               </gap> Now to ſtate the TY that will hold us both and our evaſions, that the way may be cleer deciphered in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipheration, that the meaneſt capacity may reach into, this you ſay, <hi>I</hi> am for the Law; <hi>I</hi> ſay ſo, <hi>I</hi> fay you are for the Goſpel; you ſay ſo: The ſtate i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtated, both in the ſtate pleaſed: now to prove my ſelf to be <hi>of,</hi> is not proper, but <hi>in</hi> this ſtate it muſt ſtand, for the people to underſtand. Now to prove my ſelf of the Goſpel, and you of the Law may be done, but to prove you to be of neither Goſpel nor Law neither, this ſeems ſtrange; but on the event let the people paſs ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: now <hi>I</hi> am for the Law: <hi>I</hi> anſwer, <hi>I</hi> am: now what is that Law <hi>I</hi> am for? that muſt be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that if there had been a Law given that could have given life, then righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had been by the Law:</hi> Have you a greater TY
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170905:28"/>for me then this? <hi>The Law is death:</hi> 'tis granted, what would you have more? The Law or Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice could not perfect the commers thereunto: Do you underſtand <hi>Pauls</hi> word here? 'tis well, I ſhall open them for you in another place that you know better then this, but you will bluſh to hear them: now <hi>the Law is death</hi> undeniable, elſe it could not make an in-let into a better and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſer life; whence comes this original rule, except from this, <hi>The day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt dy the death?</hi> What death this is, muſt be known; is it the death of our <hi>fleſh,</hi> and of our <hi>ſpirit?</hi> It is; how then to give life? to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned within the ſpirit in our ſpirit: What is that? Life eternal; <hi>to know him is life eternal: Fleſh and bloud cannot inberit eternal life,</hi> ſo ſaith the Text: 'tis true, but this doth not cleer the point: Once more, <hi>Sin is death,</hi> it is made by and of us, for we &amp; it are from God, but not in God; now to ſtate the Law is death, but how? in diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and for diſobedience, it layeth hold, &amp; its deſtruction of us, is to give us a better being: thus we reſting on the Law is death, becauſe it is a name of a thing, not the thing, but pointing unto another thing: The Goſpel is the ſame, the name is not the thing, but pointing us unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: thus theſe in this ſtate are one, for they are both but letteted names of one very ſame thing entire in it ſelf, that is, God; for ſaith the Law, <hi>Do thus,</hi> the Goſpel, <hi>thus;</hi> That ſaying can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give us ability of doing, and in doing is the true delarative of that that is done in us; for ſo
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170905:28"/>long as we ſay; we are names, as the Law is a name, the Goſpel is a name, but doing is the thing; now what thing is that they call for? <hi>Love;</hi> love why? where is love, there is no law: <hi>Love is the fulflling the Law:</hi> Love is <hi>Goſpel</hi> it ſelf, and <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf: why then, where love is, there is neither law nor Goſpel, it is it ſelf, and that ſelf is <hi>Jehovah;</hi> thus are we one with him through love in the eternal Spirit. Now my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to your declaratives, Are ye as ye ſay? I cannot ſay it, ye abound; how many in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of your incloſures in want? this is not love: How many have loſt their lives by your ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation, for your fetching about your own purpoſes? Have you not ſaid and unſaid? this is not the leſſon of Chriſts teaching; no it is a declarative of your acts, that that ſays tongue thou lyeſt: and to the people you have a way, that you will not let them know; for you ſay one thing, and do another: Is this the light of your Goſpel? I deſire not to partake with you in this. Now to prove you <hi>Jews,</hi> that as you term it, is a declarative; well, now to be an in-let into you, one more, this help I give you ye <hi>Jews,</hi> the Prieſts were valiant men; now I know not how you will prove, for a coward ſhows not before he comes to be tryed, and now I ſee you are har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſed with the ancient heroick weapons, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſpirit be in the cask or no, I leave to time to make manifeſt: Is this Chriſts Goſpel of peace? Ye are Jews, for Chriſt convered none with a ſword, to preach to them in another
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170905:29"/>world; I like not that Goſpel: but I am afraid that when the time comes you have one preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, an innocent man to lead up to ſave you from danger, elſe you have loſt your old trade in all times: if it did well, then the Prieſts hand was in it; but ill, that is took not well, the Prieſt had another hole to creep out at; and indeed, the people in all ages have been ſet on by you, you clap your hands, &amp; the people fall together by the ears; when they are at it for your quarrel, you will be ſure to ſave your ſelves, and clap one another, and by their fall raiſe your ſelves; but God hath cut you in <hi>England,</hi> but not down: Now to tell you plainly, the name of a <hi>Jew</hi> ye hate, the name of a Preacher of the Goſpel by acts you deny; So now, you are in effect neither Jews nor Goſpellers, yet both Jewes and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, that is indeed <hi>Heathens;</hi> for the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentile is a Heathen, the unbelieving Jew is a Heathen; for there's but light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the whole Creation: now know that to this great work that God is bringing about, there is many men fitting; as this day from an unlearn'd man that is in the work, came a letter wrote in the <hi>Indian, Greek, Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Latine,</hi> of which languages he knows not one word, but thus dear brother, and the next is Greek, and ſo carryed on that his name is not to it: Are we thus, and the world aſleep? Sirs, the day is neer, <hi>Return, why will ye dy and be deſtroyed?</hi> When was the like in the whole Creation? not ſince the earth was; there is like to be the greateſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170905:29"/>that ever came unce men inhabited the Globe; the great day is at hand that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied ſo long ago; <hi>The Earth ſhall burn as an Oven, and all the wicked and ungodly ſhall be as ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this flame: Conſider all ye proua that are lifted up and forget God, he's a coming to take vengeance on all ungodly men. Alah alamanach, alvah aſanah ab ſi Herocloch abſalamons in ſomanu in arorarum ſolamana acklah abdonarielalo ſanatar alma roi delit meco:</hi> This is wrote in the Tartarian tongue in the Eaſt <hi>Armenia</hi> from the Hebrew <hi>Radaxes,</hi> the third deſcent in that language from the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: <hi>Salu ablah vocoalis: High wo and alas is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len upon the Inhabitants of Oppreſſors, for</hi> Jehovah <hi>will thunder vengeance in a flame of whirl-wind, on and upon the rebellious ſons of men; for iniquity is great before the Lord, a conſumption is coming to conſume all that is not.</hi> Now I beſeech you, ſome of the words are brought down to your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that are more properly rendred in its own ſenſe, but them you could not underſtand; that <hi>high wo,</hi> is the cauſe of <hi>mans alas,</hi> as he is fleſh, for the affliction makes us cry <hi>is fallen:</hi> you may ſay, if it were fallen, as you ſay, we ſhould ſee it: Gods decree is done, though it fall not many yeers after. <hi>It is,</hi> that is, it is decreed, 'tis fallen now, for <hi>Jehovah</hi> will hear: 'tis the <hi>preſent tenſe</hi> and the <hi>furture tenſe</hi> ſtated; thus, to make it good; <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>future</hi> are all one to the Lord, but the <hi>preſent</hi> is ſtated, <hi>It is;</hi> and the future impeads the <hi>preſent;</hi> this is the reaſon; 'tis for the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ſakes they know all, hearing this the decree
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170905:30"/>is ſeal'd, and it is his mercy in with-holding his decree, while his people is gathered out, for the ſpirit that ſpeaks to them, is the ſame with it that ſpeaks; as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>My ſheep hear my voice, but a ſtranger they will not hear;</hi> to you it is given to know the myſterie of the Kingdom: now know all you that read this book, it is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle that a man unlearned ſhould reach ſuch a diſcovery; I anſwer again, what is it that light reaches not? Once more, I am but pen-man, and to think any thing of me, you do me wrong and your ſelf, if any thing you retain or admire, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to him that it belongs to, that is, my God: and if you ſee your God; to him be glory, I am his, and your brother to ſerve you in love, which is the Goſpel which is Chriſt, which is God in the Trinity in Unity, worſhip him alone. Now to come toward a concluſion, for my appointed time of three daies is out that I have been a part from men, and wrote hard; now beloved, I ſhall ſhew you my method in a ſhort ſcope, for my time is Gods time; not when I will, but when he pleaſes, then I write: Now I <hi>theaurau John</hi> ſhow my heart, <hi>John</hi> is the alluſe in that name: that name God gave me by voice, ſaying, <hi>Theau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rau John my ſervant, I have choſen thee:</hi> judge by this book whoſe I am: But for <hi>John,</hi> he's a Dove, he's the beloved Diſciple, the higheſt for myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; what is all this? 'tis love; what is love? Love is God. O I could dwell here in repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe words, Beloved God is Love:</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170905:30"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>So ſaid my Brother</hi> John, <hi>his Eagles EY,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had the high light in the Divine myſter ie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He from that Imperial Throne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Declar at the glory of Union:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O Unions variety,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis</hi> ſuper, ſuper, ſuper <hi>tranſcendancy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis divine, Evangelical,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the glory Cileſtial,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the pavement of our God in glory bright,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alwaies a Day, there is no night:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis Sun, 'tis Moon, 'tis Stars, and all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This is not half Celeſtial.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A greater glory I poor</hi> John <hi>did ſee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My ey is there, I ſee Eternity:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But I poor</hi> John <hi>in this Houſe of Clay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My comfort is, the ends my way</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Unto that glorious Imperial Throne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where I ſhall reigne in Union:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O then my ſorrows then ſhall ceaſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That on and in me now ſo faſt increaſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O were not that pitcht in mine ey,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I ſhould faint in my miſery.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My friends, you read theſe names, to you they be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From me full words in Miſerie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The higheſt light, the moſt in tears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Becauſe he's drenching forth from fears.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>But to return, I had almoſt loſt my ſelf in expreſſing the Sea of trouble I ly under: <hi>Love, Love, Love,</hi> O my Beloved, how lovely are ye being in love! Why love turns all things into
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170905:31"/>it ſelf; turns hatred, envie, malice, murder, it turns all theſe, and more into it ſelf; this is love! 'Tis the Philoſophers ſtone, that turns all into its <hi>inclu,</hi> this love there is no end in it, no begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, no middle, no part, 'tis one, 'tis all, 'tis all things; this all, and one, and all things, is God, then to be Gods, is to love; O love one another that this envie may have no being amongſt you, nor in you. O that ye would be but your ſelves, then you would be love; now when you are not in love, you are not your ſelves: Love is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration from death to life. Would you have a reſurrection? 'tis love, or never, or no heaven; love purchaſes all, payes all, unties all, and ties all: Love, there is no ſpeaking of it, for 'tis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, 'tis tranſcendant mans mouth to utter, the Evangelical voices are too narrow to expreſs love; I could dwell here for ever and ever, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get off from this rock: Love is the fulfilling of the Law, the obedience of the Goſpel, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let to eternal bleſſedneſs for ever, which without love, no bleſſedneſs, but the wrath of God abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on us for ever <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>A lab</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hoſaret</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſalvah</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Creation God in himſelf, and the Creation in it ſelf, and both in himſelf, that is <hi>Jehovah</hi> himſelf in himſelf, there is the firſt perfection of the excellency of <hi>Hamah,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170905:31"/>your <hi>Adam,</hi> that is Man, and all things with him in ſtrength; this is the feigned Paradiſe and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in <hi>Eden; Eden</hi> is falſe wrote, for the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficants, that is Creations, cannot be tied to one place or garden, for the <hi>multiplicity</hi> cannot be confined to any one place, except it be radically intendant in himſelf, for his glory he will not give to any other, neither undignifying himſelf, ſo as to have his royal preheminence confined in any one thing, for you cannot ſpeak any one properly, but God he is one, and all things to him are one, but not ſo in themſelves properly or eſſentially, but in him all is one, was one, and to come is the ſame, for <hi>Jehovah</hi> cyphered is the union his name, the intent of <hi>Eden</hi> is the ſame, but not rightly underſtood, for <hi>Eden</hi> cuts thus; <hi>Eden</hi> ought to have been <hi>Edenei, Eden</hi> is no lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as I have wrote, but 'tis a divine <hi>Siphirates</hi> of <hi>Siphrates, Siphrates</hi> them three are the ſame with <hi>Edeneiii,</hi> for the meaning of the Eternity operating in it ſelf, then where can any bar or ſtop be ſet, for you cannot write an influ with a TY in the laſt letter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Nun</hi> is a bar in any place except ſhe be the radical, or leader in any ſtate, <hi>Henok,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ahlu, Hene,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ophrono, pallu</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Peked,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Philiades oli oko araret alvah
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170905:32"/>deat ſem hu hanri alvah pear</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ralu</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in ſe ſahatt oan verriko bele in hury peata perati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt decipherative is <hi>Jehovah:</hi> Now all People, Tongues, and Languages, know that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi> is all over all, and evermore the ſame, the beginning, no time; the all, no place, all places in one place, and all times in one time, and that time is the time of all times, and yet he no time; this is he that rules and reigns in eternity: this is deciphered <hi>Jehovah</hi> his name, &amp; to it obedience is the ſame. I <hi>Theaurau John Tanniour Allah al,</hi> hi-Prieſt ſend greeting to my brethren both Jews and Gentiles, the perfect declarative of the firſt ſtate, but no time or yeers, neither is there time or yeers with him, that is all time and yeers, but this is to let you and all people know, that there is now a reſtoring the people to a pure lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, for this thing am I come forth, fitted with light and divine knowledge in the depth of depths, to unſeal that ſealed book, and Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical light that lies wrapped in the womb of the ſo called Law and Goſpel, <hi>in ſe ſerta reſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>obederat alma honaſa huli penerati alvah ableuviſſe in ſe locat amarviſſem humanet rokoas ſalah azaret eltah alvah hon ono olephad in ſe mori melet ori neri
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170905:32"/>maleorei onoriko olo ophons narratus aſa ſardoas lobcim olet ammi Phikepead ebelleier elma hoſai in re meat olko ephrae peata alvah huri apanari in ſem tulat in meadti amanet oliko abſalem inter amaferet oko aſani alvah poi kopo pion inreſenalis in re pekat valuah Jahalu pai kau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam abſemuiſſe pelet amen oli veat anta onarial al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah allet hoko nederem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in ſem tion valvah pie deneat valko ophinoiei pheredet pelko moneta ſeab tola mem in ſi lota phalla in poneie polik a vet dina inter ſe pokuneri olo bonoſe ſeem alvah oli olimalto onori pikuat remi moli poliat nem inteler lota valla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lua meat oliriko in lobemus avar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in ſi meam in loca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus allah vallue anakatur ablat pheniolue adna apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let homen in teu oat alto moſiſere verat adma liel pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ovouvet odo moli aſaderet manialta viat ono ponri opaalet honoſoophroriko in laniah mempala verat olo peat ſalvah eri nedet hen mei abalet hoſaret addi me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let verko oli milet voko monſa anni pieti pel odi lode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ata in ri pei pel pelta tianna mam ori de let adma pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu lah atti nedet tuolo omen ſatar ollo adma oſonet pek hoſarret.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here Learnings Learning you may ſee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'I is carried on Alphabetically;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And yet no Alphabet you ſee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But 'tis the Divineſt Myſtery.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So in tricable are all his waies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That man his paintings cannot praiſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Now my Brethren, God according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which promiſe is himſelf, hath ſent his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative to the Inliabitants in and upon the Globe, and in, and upon the influences, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flues
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170905:33"/>the intricables varietie in and upon the ſame, that is the whole created by him: Now as is expreſſed before: I am <hi>Reuben</hi> the Lords <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this new Creation, and the firſt in the firſt Trine, deſcending in <hi>vive voſe &amp; in Evangelorum ſem in phratris regi pecavit, non vita ſed enim vita eſt mors omnibus hominibus in loco al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat obiremus in ſolat peco ori ſem abtracte in diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience;</hi> the Engliſh is, <hi>Man is fallen to nothing by light,</hi> that is <hi>vita, life:</hi> Now you may ſay, How can light cauſe man to fall to nothing? I anſwer, Light doth not cauſe man to fall to nothing, but that man is nothing by that light; as thus, man ſees temporals, they ſee him, for ſight is not in man, but in the object that he ſees to effect: now to be properly ſaid to ſee, none nor nothing can be ſaid to ſee but God only; he is our ſight if we ſee; if not; we ſee not: thus in ſeeing, we ſee not, and in hearing, we underſtand not, for not to be in light, is death, and not to be; one more, now in him that is light we are, were, and ſhall be light, out darkneſs is this vail we are in: now to come to the eſſential ſtate of man, in his firſt ſtate that was innocency, ſo 'tis named, now to prove that name innocency, we muſt conſider what created hath relation to, that is the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of man and all things; How was man inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent? thus, he was nothing, and to be nothing is pure innocency, that was when we were not; when was that? when there was no God; when was that? never; for know God could not be,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170905:33"/>if not alwaies the ſame; thus I prove, that that comes to act after, is for want of knowledge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and that that was before, cannot act behind, which is time, times, time: look well into your own riddle in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> you ſee that he ſtood not at all, but detracted and fell you ſay, ſo ſay I; thus his very being in fleſh was his fall, and he became like a beaſt that periſheth: how, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that his body now is and was beaſt-like, for 'tis ſaid, <hi>skubulo,</hi> but dung: you are miſtaken to think this groſs elementary ſubſtance is your bodies, alas this is hell; your body is another thing, you are priſoned here, and your reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is at going out of this hell to thoſe para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daical bodies bodied in him that is <hi>Jeſus, Jehovah Adoniel, L, Jah, Eloah, Aove, Tele, Throon, God the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I ceaſe, and cannot open this ſtate, nor tranſlate them languages that are cited, but in my next book I ſhall open them, that I am ſure of, but the time I know not, till he that is my light ſet up in me himſelf, he is my light, life, glory: glory to him which was, and is, and is to come, the <hi>Jehovah</hi> omnipotent, <hi>Amen;</hi> no <hi>Amen</hi> to him, we ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> but includes that that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be included, the Myſtery is to come.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="authors_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:34"/>
            <p>I <hi>Theaurau John</hi> the Jew, of the Tribe of <hi>Reuben,</hi> of the ſeed of <hi>David</hi> according to the fleſh and ſpirit, wrote this Book, onely the Epiſtle I wrote not; Now if any man or men be not ſatisfied in all, or part, or parts of the part, I am willing in the humility of my ſpirit to render an account in writing; for I have an impead in my ſpeech: and this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour I require, which in Juſtice ought not to be denyed me being the Commoner of <hi>England.</hi> Now let no man judge this book leſt he be judged by the things therein contained: for I am ſent forth for the gathering the Jews my Brethren home ye ſay you pray for; time will manifeſt it whether it be in truth or not; I know the Lord will gather them, as he hath ſpoken by all the Prophets, and the time is now come that they ſhall be reſtored into their glorious Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the tranſcendant excellent ſtately ſtate that that ancient people my Brethren ſhall be ſtated in, even in their own land, as the Lord hath ſhown me. Once more judge not.</p>
            <p>Blind men cannot diſcern colours, but the ſeeing Ey ſees all things, as they are, not as they ſeem; mind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Selat ory a ſaba arry nedat me:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Divine light cannot be meaſured by Human Learning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arry ſele oli ſapuit nedat mecum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor the Divine Light ſtoop to mans capacity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Id est vita non ſolemus in rem faſit</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeing ey ſees it ſelf all things, we nothing in the thing.</p>
            <p>Hereunto <hi>I</hi> have ſet my hand and ſeal, <hi>Theaurau John</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tannjour Allah Al Sabbah Skribahjail.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>THough this Book was Licenſed according to Law and Command, yet contrary to that Law, it was hindred till this 25. of <hi>February,</hi> I could not get it Printed. 1650.</p>
            <p>Oh this WILL, <hi>Not,</hi> LAW, overthrows the Nations Foundation.</p>
            <p>This book is to be ſold at the Stationers in common, and at the three golden Lyons without Temple-bar, you may have them, or hear where they are to be had.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a sickle next to a blazon or coat of arms with three horizontal stripes</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:34"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Downame.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170905:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome interruptions in the Printing this Treatiſe, together with the abſence of the Maſter-printer, hath occaſioned many errors, eſpecially in the firſt part thereof, the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial thou ſhalt find here corrected to thy hand, thoſe leſſer miſtakes, and ſome pointings, be pleaſed to mend with thy pen as thou readeſt.</p>
            <p>IN the firſt Epiſtle page 1. line 23, for whee, read where, p. 2. l. 11. for Iſas, r. Jeſus, p. 3. l. 9, for onely hold, r. onely both hold. In the third page of the Treatiſe, line 19. for preſident, r. precedent, p. 6. l. 15. for he heart, r. the heart, l. 18. for you name, r. your name, p. 7. l. 22. for to indetractation, r. too inderractation, p. 9. l. 4. for verſe 10 r. verſe 3. l. 24. r. and ſhall be, light the ſame, p 13. for unbeers. r. unbelievers, p. 14. l. 13. r. they being not in the being, and leave out is light, p. 16. l. 20. r. ought to be paid, p. 17. l. 1. for diſpute. r. diſputes p. 23 l. 31. for quiet, r quite, l. 31. for his Ideny, r. this Ideny, p. 30. l. 10. where you find it luma, r. lama. and after mecavi, inſert theſe letters, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 35. l. 10. for Thuſali, r. Thus Ali, p. 39. l. 16. r. te skubulo ſed skubulo orcat in ſe, p. 40. l. 29. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 43. l. 27. for hears, r. hearers.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
